<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Blockchain on Ex Machina</title>
    <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/tags/blockchain/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Blockchain on Ex Machina</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://rahulmatthan.github.io/tags/blockchain/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Casino or Computer</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/20/03/2024/casino-or-computer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/20/03/2024/casino-or-computer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://rahulmatthan.github.io/images/computer-or-casino.jpg&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cryptocurrency regulation has, so far, focussed on been on the mitigating the risk to speculative investors. But there is a far more important innovation that is embeded into the architecture and design of modern crypto currency. This is what regulators should be looking to better understand.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Proof of Humanness</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/23/08/2023/proof-of-humanness/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/23/08/2023/proof-of-humanness/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://rahulmatthan.github.io/images/proof-of-humanness.png&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Worldcoin has been designed to address the concern that in a world saturated with artificial intelligence we are going to need a proof of humanness. As true as that might be, I believe we need to go much further. And also tackle truth in content.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Unified Ledger</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/01/03/2023/the-unified-ledger/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/01/03/2023/the-unified-ledger/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://rahulmatthan.github.io/images/unified-ledger.png&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Central Bank Digital Currencies (CBDCs) and the tokenization of private money deposits could revolutionize the financial system. Agustin Carstens suggests a unified digital ledger for both public and private digital money, enabling efficiencies like smart contracts and instant settlements. This approach could extend to tokenizing various assets, transforming governance by embedding compliance within transactions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sufficient Decentralisation</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/07/12/2022/sufficient-decentralisation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/07/12/2022/sufficient-decentralisation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://rahulmatthan.github.io/images/sufficient-decentralisation.jpg&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We need to think about creating &amp;ldquo;sufficiently decentralized&amp;rdquo; social networks. While decentralization offers more control to users, it has drawbacks - such as non-unique usernames across the network. If we can use smart contracts to create a decentralized name registry we might be able to balance user control and functionality, and create a more user-empowered internet.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A New Digital Coin</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/12/07/2022/a-new-digital-coin/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/12/07/2022/a-new-digital-coin/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We need to understand how Central Bank Digital Currencies (CBDCs) fit into the modern 2-tiered banking system. While CBDCs offer potential benefits, such as banking the unbanked, do we even need a CBDC in the Indian context.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Virtually Mine</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/15/03/2022/virtually-mine/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/15/03/2022/virtually-mine/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There has been an evolution of ownership from physical objects to digital assets - despite the limitations of digital ownership. Flow, a new blockchain technology, and Cadence, a programming language, together may enable true ownership of digital assets, in a way that mirrors physical ownership.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Crypto Regulation</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/07/12/2021/crypto-regulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/07/12/2021/crypto-regulation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cryptocurrency regulation will have to address a number of issues. To address the fact that cryptocurrencies provide anonymity, regulations can ensure that crypto exchanges conduct customer verification checks and be trained on anti-money laundering. The exchanges themselves can be required to be registered in India to fall within the ambit of Indian law. To address taxation concerns, our laws can be amended to base the tax payable on the fair market value of cryptocurrency as on the date of payment or receipt. Any offers of cryptocurrency can be required to comply with disclosure requirements for investor protection. All this can be achieved by amending existing laws and does not need a new regulation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Future of Title</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/29/09/2021/the-future-of-title/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/29/09/2021/the-future-of-title/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The cutting edge of innovation in NFTs is taking place in the gaming space. Most NFT based games use non-fungible tokens to attest the title of in-game digital assets. If we start to use the metaverse for more and more real world activities, we will need some way to assert title over digital assets. NFT&amp;rsquo;s could become the future of title in the metaverse.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Non Fungible Tokens</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/06/04/2021/non-fungible-tokens/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 06 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/06/04/2021/non-fungible-tokens/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;NFTs are digital tokens that represent ownership in an underlying asset. At present they are a means by which to monetise digital art but eventually they will become the digital bridge that various commercial applications need for monetisation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The CBDC Alternative</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/03/2021/the-cbdc-alternative/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 16 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/03/2021/the-cbdc-alternative/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bitcoin should not be treated as a currency. But at the same time it should not be banned. Cryptocurrencies are permissionless systems that operate without intermediaries. As a result central banks cannot implement macro-economic measures in the event of a financial crisis. However, they are programable and can be incorporated into smart contracts offering a number of opportunities for digital financial inclusion. CBDCs are the best of both worlds combining the programability of bitcoin with the stability of fiat currency.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What the top court’s order means for virtual currencies</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/18/03/2020/what-the-top-courts-order-means-for-virtual-currencies/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/18/03/2020/what-the-top-courts-order-means-for-virtual-currencies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Supreme Court of India ruled that the Reserve Bank of India (RBI) has the authority to regulate virtual currencies but found its decision to ban regulated entities from providing services to virtual currency exchanges disproportionate. The ruling clears the way for RBI to issue specific regulations on cryptocurrencies, likely more stringent than those in other countries, recognizing the potential stronger adverse effects on India&amp;rsquo;s developing economy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>UPI is world-class and it’s time to take it international</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/24/07/2019/upi-is-world-class-and-its-time-to-take-it-international/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/24/07/2019/upi-is-world-class-and-its-time-to-take-it-international/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;While cryptocurrencies like Bitcoin and Facebook&amp;rsquo;s Libra can enable efficient cross-border transfers, India&amp;rsquo;s existing UPI system, with its robust digital payments infrastructure, already meets the country&amp;rsquo;s needs and can be internationalized without relying on blockchain technologies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The futility of prohibiting bitcoin trade</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/25/04/2018/the-futility-of-prohibiting-bitcoin-trade/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/25/04/2018/the-futility-of-prohibiting-bitcoin-trade/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Reserve Bank of India (RBI) has banned regulated entities from providing services related to virtual currencies, citing concerns over consumer protection, market integrity, and money laundering. I question the necessity of this step, since the perceived anonymity of bitcoin transactions can be penetrated. What&amp;rsquo;s more, the ban may drive nefarious activities further underground, making them harder to detect. I suggest improving forensic skills might be a more effective approach.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Bitcoin and the law of centralization</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/20/12/2017/bitcoin-and-the-law-of-centralization/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/20/12/2017/bitcoin-and-the-law-of-centralization/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The evolution of internet access in India, from a single-user bulletin board service to the vast, decentralized web, mirrors a broader trend towards centralization in digital services. Despite the internet&amp;rsquo;s expansive possibilities, most users gravitate towards a few familiar sites. This centralization tendency is also evident in Bitcoin&amp;rsquo;s blockchain technology, where mining pools&amp;rsquo; dominance challenges the decentralized ideal, highlighting the need for potential regulatory intervention or system redesign.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blockchain Land Records</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/06/2017/blockchain-land-records/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/06/2017/blockchain-land-records/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Real estate transactions in India are complex due to difficulties in confirming property titles. The Torrens system, offering indefeasible title guarantees, could revolutionize this, as seen in Rajasthan&amp;rsquo;s new legislation. Implementing blockchain technology for land records could ensure tamper-proof, transparent, and efficient property transactions, modernizing the archaic system.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cutting out the Middleman</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/08/06/2017/cutting-out-the-middleman/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/08/06/2017/cutting-out-the-middleman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Music&amp;rsquo;s evolution from live performances to digital streaming has been shaped by technology, expanding audience reach but often at the cost of artist revenue. With the advent of blockchain-based services like Musicoin, artists can now bypass traditional intermediaries, offering direct access to their music and potentially transforming the industry&amp;rsquo;s revenue model.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blockchain Governance</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/13/07/2016/blockchain-governance/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/13/07/2016/blockchain-governance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bitcoin&amp;rsquo;s distributed ledger technology offers a solution to the trust issue in online transactions, eliminating the need for intermediaries in e-commerce. This blockchain concept can extend beyond currency, revolutionizing contracts, intellectual property rights, and public records by ensuring tamper-resistant, verifiable transactions. Governments could adopt this technology for more efficient, accountable public services, as seen in Rajasthan&amp;rsquo;s state-guaranteed land titles, potentially paving the way for blockchain governance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
