<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Health on Ex Machina</title><link>https://exmachina.in/tags/health/</link><description>Recent content in Health on Ex Machina</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://exmachina.in/tags/health/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Rare Disease Platform</title><link>https://exmachina.in/09/07/2025/rare-disease-platform/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Jul 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/09/07/2025/rare-disease-platform/</guid><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/rare-disease-platform.jpg" width="auto"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Most rare diseases are had to treat because the economies of scale just aren&amp;rsquo;t favourable. However, since they are of genetic origin, it should be possible to leverage the breakthroughs we&amp;rsquo;ve made in genetic engineering to find effective solutions. Since India has a number of endogamous communities, the data we can contribute could be extremely valuable.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Secondary Use of Health Data</title><link>https://exmachina.in/18/12/2024/secondary-use-of-health-data/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/18/12/2024/secondary-use-of-health-data/</guid><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/secondary-use-of-health-data.jpg" width="auto"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;While it is generally advisable to anonymise health data, doing so at population scale would allow us benefit from secondary usese of data. The ABDM envisages this but by additionally deploying Secure Data Environments it should be possible to augment the level of data protection.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Micro Robots</title><link>https://exmachina.in/10/01/2024/micro-robots/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/10/01/2024/micro-robots/</guid><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/micro-robots.jpg" width="auto"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The idea of micro-robots is about to make the transition from science fiction to science fact. But before we can take advantage of all that this new technology has to offer we will need to consider the various legal, ethical and societal concerns that this new technology can raise.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Studying Human Infection</title><link>https://exmachina.in/02/08/2023/studying-human-infection/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/02/08/2023/studying-human-infection/</guid><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/studying-human-infection.png" width="auto"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The practice of infecting human subjects with disease under controlled circumstances to better understand how the body reacts to a new treatment is as old as medical science itself. The reason why it is not common in India is because of ethical and legal concerns. If we can find our way past that this could be a useful approach.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Neither Good Nor Bad</title><link>https://exmachina.in/05/07/2023/neither-good-nor-bad/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/05/07/2023/neither-good-nor-bad/</guid><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/neither-good-nor-bad.png" width="auto"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We tend to think of technology as either “good” nor “bad” based on the outcomes it has. This is futile as in most instances any harms that may be caused by technology is on account of how it is used and by whom.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Rule Makers</title><link>https://exmachina.in/31/05/2023/rule-makers/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/31/05/2023/rule-makers/</guid><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/rule-makers.png" width="auto"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We have, for most of our existence as a nation, accepted the governance frameworks that have already been implemented elsewhere in the world. With digital public infrastructure India is, perhaps for the first time, making the rules. It is time for us to stop being rule-takers and assume the role of rule-makers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>In-Built Bias</title><link>https://exmachina.in/24/05/2023/in-built-bias/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/24/05/2023/in-built-bias/</guid><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/in-built-bias.png" width="auto"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;When healthcare is powered by artificial intelligence and smart devices, we must ensure that all of humanity stands to benefit. We need open, transparent and customisable algorithms in our hardware.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Phages and Precision Medicine</title><link>https://exmachina.in/01/12/2021/phages-and-precision-medicine/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/01/12/2021/phages-and-precision-medicine/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Bacteriophages target specific bacterial cells and destroy them leaving all other cells unharmed. These organisms have been used for phage therapy - a treatment for disease that involves administering the specific bacteriophage corresponding to a given bacterial infection in order to treat it. Now that the continuous use of broad spectrum antibiotics has resulted in superbugs with high levels of antibiotic resistance, phage therapy might be the precision medicine solution that we need. This will require us to overhaul our current thinking about pharmaceuticals and adopt more localised manufacture.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Patient Capital</title><link>https://exmachina.in/23/06/2021/patient-capital/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/23/06/2021/patient-capital/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Breakthroughs in science require patient capital that must be provided by the government. Scientists need to be given a long rope and not be held to the standards of accountability to which we typically hold the government. They need to have bipartisan [[political support]] as they operate at time-scales beyond that which politicians normally function within. They need pipelines to market that will allow these ideas to be naturally commercialised.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Rural Challenge</title><link>https://exmachina.in/18/05/2021/the-rural-challenge/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/18/05/2021/the-rural-challenge/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We need different protocols to deal with the pandemic in rural India. Instead of supplying oxygen we need to provide them with a supply of medicines and basic equipment they need. Since it is not feasible to get RTPCR tests done in a reasonable time frame we need to replace that with syndromic testing using oximeters and thermometers. And we need to leverage our decentralised healthcare networks.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Vaccine Waiver</title><link>https://exmachina.in/04/05/2021/the-vaccine-waiver/</link><pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/04/05/2021/the-vaccine-waiver/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Given the urgency to vaccinate the world there is an urgent need to ramp up production of vaccines. All that is coming in the way of that is the intellectual property rights over vaccine recipes. What is required is a temporary vaccine waiver of intellectual property rights in order to encourage worldwide manufacture.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Vaccinate</title><link>https://exmachina.in/28/04/2021/vaccinate/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/28/04/2021/vaccinate/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We must combat vaccine hesitancy and get everyone vaccinated against covid-19. The only strategy to survive in India is to not get infected or to get fully vaccinated. The risk of blood clots is insignificant compared to the risk of getting the disease.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Cost of Orphan Drugs</title><link>https://exmachina.in/30/09/2020/the-cost-of-orphan-drugs/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/30/09/2020/the-cost-of-orphan-drugs/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Karanveer Singh has Duchenne&amp;rsquo;s Muscular Dystrophy (DMD). His family has discovered an experimental therapy that skips the missing exon in the DMD gene, allowing dystrophin production. Despite bureaucratic obstacles, the Central Licensing Authority permitted a clinical trial across India. If successful, the treatment, developed by the Dystrophy Annihilation Research Trust (DART), will be available at a fraction of the cost of Western alternatives, offering hope to thousands of families.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The mission to put health records at doctors fingertips</title><link>https://exmachina.in/12/08/2020/the-mission-to-put-health-records-at-doctors-fingertips/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/12/08/2020/the-mission-to-put-health-records-at-doctors-fingertips/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The National Digital Health Mission&amp;rsquo;s Strategy Overview outlines India&amp;rsquo;s plan to become a Digital Health Nation, leveraging the nascent state of healthcare digitization to learn from other countries and avoid their mistakes. The strategy involves adapting India&amp;rsquo;s data portability architecture, using the Data Empowerment and Protection Architecture (DEPA) for healthcare data sharing. It proposes a radically-federated design, storing healthcare data at its generation point and enabling rapid data transfer across the health system.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Immunity passports might be inevitable as we go along</title><link>https://exmachina.in/17/06/2020/immunity-passports-might-be-inevitable-as-we-go-along/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/17/06/2020/immunity-passports-might-be-inevitable-as-we-go-along/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As countries grapple with COVID-19&amp;rsquo;s community spread phase, the focus has shifted to frequent testing. It is time to consider the potential use of health and immunity passports. These passports could become essential for travel and social activities, but at the same time give rise to a greater risk of deepening social divides and creating new forms of privilege.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>How the covid pandemic could reshape life in our cities</title><link>https://exmachina.in/20/05/2020/how-the-covid-pandemic-could-reshape-life-in-our-cities/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/20/05/2020/how-the-covid-pandemic-could-reshape-life-in-our-cities/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Cities are dense hubs of economic activity. However when they come up against an epidemic like COVID-19, it prompts rethinking urban design, emphasizing remote work, local markets, and reduced physical contact, while considering the impact on migrant populations and urban efficiency.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Aarogya Setu and the value of syndromic surveillance</title><link>https://exmachina.in/13/05/2020/aarogya-setu-and-the-value-of-syndromic-surveillance/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/13/05/2020/aarogya-setu-and-the-value-of-syndromic-surveillance/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The 2001 anthrax attacks led to the development of syndromic surveillance, a method for early disease detection using aggregated data. This technique, exemplified by India&amp;rsquo;s Aarogya Setu app during COVID-19, analyzes symptom data and location history to predict and manage outbreaks, balancing public health benefits with privacy concerns.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Mobility datasets could help India exit the lockdown</title><link>https://exmachina.in/22/04/2020/mobility-datasets-could-help-india-exit-the-lockdown/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/22/04/2020/mobility-datasets-could-help-india-exit-the-lockdown/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;During India&amp;rsquo;s fifth week of lockdown, measures have slowed COVID-19&amp;rsquo;s spread, despite testing and reporting concerns. A staggered lifting of restrictions is planned, balancing disease control with economic needs. Utilizing mobility data can guide reopening strategies, but privacy concerns must be addressed, especially in less dense areas.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The corona crisis must not make us shut the world out</title><link>https://exmachina.in/01/04/2020/the-corona-crisis-must-not-make-us-shut-the-world-out/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/01/04/2020/the-corona-crisis-must-not-make-us-shut-the-world-out/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The COVID-19 pandemic exposed the vulnerabilities of global supply chains and our over-reliance on just-in-time delivery models. While some may argue for more insular approaches and increased governmental control, the free movement of data and international collaboration has enabled rapid responses, such as genome sequencing and 3D printing of medical equipment. The crisis highlights the potential for global collaboration to impact health outcomes positively.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Platform technologies could deliver a vaccine quickly</title><link>https://exmachina.in/03/03/2020/platform-technologies-could-deliver-a-vaccine-quickly/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/03/03/2020/platform-technologies-could-deliver-a-vaccine-quickly/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Developing vaccines is expensive, risky, and time-consuming due to stringent approval processes and logistical challenges. Platform technologies for vaccines, which can be adapted quickly for different pathogens, offer a promising solution. However, current legal regimes are not equipped to evaluate these platforms, and regulators must gain experience with them to accelerate approvals.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Forensic DNA technology and the miasma of distrust</title><link>https://exmachina.in/11/09/2019/forensic-dna-technology-and-the-miasma-of-distrust/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/11/09/2019/forensic-dna-technology-and-the-miasma-of-distrust/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;British colonial India significantly advanced forensic science, driven by a narrative of native deceit. Techniques like graphology and serological analysis were developed as judicial reliance on forensics grew, due to distrust in native testimonies. This legacy persists in India&amp;rsquo;s criminal justice system, often prioritizing technology over fundamental rights, as seen in recent DNA data bank legislation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The dilemma of trying out new cures for malaria</title><link>https://exmachina.in/13/03/2019/the-dilemma-of-trying-out-new-cures-for-malaria/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/13/03/2019/the-dilemma-of-trying-out-new-cures-for-malaria/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The alarming rise of drug-resistant malaria in South-East Asia necessitates the development of new treatment regimes in India. Controlled human infection model (CHIM) studies could expedite this process but raise significant ethical concerns. A robust ethical and regulatory framework is essential to proceed with such studies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Manufacturing drugs on demand</title><link>https://exmachina.in/12/12/2018/manufacturing-drugs-on-demand/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/12/12/2018/manufacturing-drugs-on-demand/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The intricate, global supply chains and specialized production processes in modern industry, poses challenges - especially in pharmaceutical manufacturing, where supply chain disruptions can be life-threatening. Recent developments in continuous, on-demand drug manufacturing, like MIT&amp;rsquo;s compact synthesis unit, offer revolutionary solutions but clash with current regulatory frameworks, necessitating regulatory adaptation to embrace these technological advancements.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The downside of gene editing</title><link>https://exmachina.in/05/12/2018/the-downside-of-gene-editing/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/05/12/2018/the-downside-of-gene-editing/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Chinese researcher He Jiankui&amp;rsquo;s use of CRISPR-Cas9 technology to edit a human embryo has sparked international condemnation. The editing, aimed at disabling a gene to increase resistance to diseases like AIDS, raises ethical concerns, risks unforeseen consequences, and highlights the need for a formal global treaty on gene editing.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The use of technology in providing healthcare</title><link>https://exmachina.in/28/11/2018/the-use-of-technology-in-providing-healthcare/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/28/11/2018/the-use-of-technology-in-providing-healthcare/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ayushman Bharat, the world&amp;rsquo;s largest public health insurance program, aims to cover 500 million people in India. Its success depends on using technology to scale health services, monitor treatment, and ensure accountability. Despite challenges in digitizing healthcare, India has the opportunity to create a unified framework for medical data exchange, prioritizing patient rights, privacy, and cross-platform accessibility.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Genetic matchmaking can improve medical outcomes</title><link>https://exmachina.in/07/11/2018/genetic-matchmaking-can-improve-medical-outcomes/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/07/11/2018/genetic-matchmaking-can-improve-medical-outcomes/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Population bottlenecks increase susceptibility to genetic diseases like Tay-Sachs. To mitigate this, initiatives like Dor Yeshorem screen for recessive genes in high-risk communities. Similar genetic risks exist in India&amp;rsquo;s endogamous groups, indicating a need for widespread genetic analysis to improve medical outcomes and potentially integrate genetic compatibility into marriage decisions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The lady with the lamp and data-driven medicine</title><link>https://exmachina.in/08/08/2018/the-lady-with-the-lamp-and-data-driven-medicine/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/08/08/2018/the-lady-with-the-lamp-and-data-driven-medicine/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Florence Nightingale&amp;rsquo;s contributions to medical science extended beyond nursing to include statistical analysis, leading to significant hospital reforms. Despite technological advancements, the medical profession still lags in adopting data technologies like AI. Regulations constraining data within national boundaries may hinder the development of these technologies.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A new direction for data privacy in healthcare</title><link>https://exmachina.in/11/04/2018/a-new-direction-for-data-privacy-in-healthcare/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/11/04/2018/a-new-direction-for-data-privacy-in-healthcare/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The draft Digital Information Security in Healthcare Act aims to regulate the use of digital health data, emphasizing patient consent and privacy. It allows anonymized data for public health research but restricts commercial use. However, its timing is questionable, as it precedes the anticipated overarching national data protection framework, potentially leading to inconsistencies in privacy regulations across sectors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Does right to life include advance directives?</title><link>https://exmachina.in/14/03/2018/does-right-to-life-include-advance-directives/</link><pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/14/03/2018/does-right-to-life-include-advance-directives/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Supreme Court has held that right to live with dignity includes within it the obligation to smoothen the process of dying for terminally ill patients who have no hope of recovery but has imposed too many bureaucratic processes on the exercise of that right.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Genetic diseases should be covered by insurance</title><link>https://exmachina.in/07/03/2018/genetic-diseases-should-be-covered-by-insurance/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/07/03/2018/genetic-diseases-should-be-covered-by-insurance/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Delhi High court has held that rejecting an insurance claim on the grounds of the genetic conditions exclusion issued by the IRDAI would be violative of violative of Article 14 since discrimination on the basis of genetic heritage is unconstitutional.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Breaking Down Data Silos</title><link>https://exmachina.in/23/08/2017/breaking-down-data-silos/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/23/08/2017/breaking-down-data-silos/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Individuals generate vast amounts of medical data through various healthcare interactions and personal devices. Machine learning can unlock proactive diagnoses, but current data silos and over-protective attitudes hinder access and sharing. A proposed electronic data request framework in India aims to place control with the data subject, enabling personal analysis and broader applications, such as credit-worthiness assessments.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Path to Self Improvement</title><link>https://exmachina.in/26/07/2017/path-to-self-improvement/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/26/07/2017/path-to-self-improvement/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Darwin&amp;rsquo;s theory of natural selection inspired Francis Galton to propose eugenics, the idea that selective breeding could enhance human traits. This concept gained traction in the early 20th century, leading to sterilization laws in the U.S. and Nazi Germany&amp;rsquo;s racial hygiene program. These ideas eventually culminated in the Holocaust, where six million Jews were killed. Today, the potential of CRISPR/Cas9 technology to alter genes offers a new frontier in genetics, with the lessons of the past serving as a cautionary reminder.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A la Carte Medicine</title><link>https://exmachina.in/12/07/2017/a-la-carte-medicine/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/12/07/2017/a-la-carte-medicine/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Dengue, that affects millions annually, may be mitigated by using Wolbachia-infected mosquitoes. This approach, along with fecal microbiota transplants for C-diff infections, underscores a shift towards microbiome-focused therapies. Future medicine may rely on synthetic biology for precise, customized treatments, challenging current regulatory frameworks.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Myth of the Average Man</title><link>https://exmachina.in/10/05/2017/the-myth-of-the-average-man/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/10/05/2017/the-myth-of-the-average-man/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We need to question the concept of &amp;ldquo;average&amp;rdquo; human medical standards, such as body temperature given the extent of the individual variations in human biology. There is a need for personalized medical treatment particularly when one considers how wearable technologies could revolutionize healthcare by enabling continuous monitoring and customized care.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The End of Life</title><link>https://exmachina.in/12/04/2017/the-end-of-life/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/12/04/2017/the-end-of-life/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There are ethical and legal complexities with treating terminally ill patients in India. There is a thin and grey line between palliative care and assisted suicide. We need clear legislation regarding living wills and the right to die with dignity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Insuring Previvors</title><link>https://exmachina.in/22/03/2017/insuring-previvors/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/22/03/2017/insuring-previvors/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The story of chess and rice illustrates exponential growth, paralleled in technology and genetics. Moore&amp;rsquo;s Law on computing power doubling every two years has led to advanced AI, machine learning, and virtual reality. Similarly, rapid advancements in genetics, outpacing Moore&amp;rsquo;s Law, are revolutionizing disease diagnosis and treatment, potentially transforming industries like insurance by redefining pre-existing conditions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Rare Diseases: Orphan Drugs</title><link>https://exmachina.in/18/01/2017/rare-diseases-orphan-drugs/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/18/01/2017/rare-diseases-orphan-drugs/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Those with rare diseases face tremendous challenges given that pharmaceutical companies have little incentive to produce the necessary drugs, and the high costs often make treatment unaffordable. Karnataka became the first state to release a Rare Diseases and Orphan Drugs Policy, recommending preventive testing, education, tax breaks, and insurance coverage for rare diseases. If other states follow suit, it could offer hope for those like Mohammed to lead longer and more dignified lives.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Big Bad Data</title><link>https://exmachina.in/11/01/2017/big-bad-data/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/11/01/2017/big-bad-data/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Statistician Fredrick Hoffman, known for identifying health risks like asbestos and tobacco, is also remembered for his flawed 1896 study claiming African Americans were inherently sicker than whites. This study, influenced by prejudice, had lasting negative impacts. As we increasingly rely on data and predictive algorithms, it&amp;rsquo;s crucial to avoid such biases and ensure fair, accurate interpretations to prevent perpetuating discrimination and injustice.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Cutting the Code with CRISPR</title><link>https://exmachina.in/23/11/2016/cutting-the-code-with-crispr/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/23/11/2016/cutting-the-code-with-crispr/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;CRISPR-Cas9 is a gene-editing breakthrough that promises cures for genetic diseases but raises ethical concerns about creating &amp;ldquo;designer babies&amp;rdquo; and potential misuse. While some advocate for a moratorium on germ-line modifications, others argue for its therapeutic potential, especially in eradicating devastating genetic disorders like Tay-Sachs.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>A Database of our Maladies</title><link>https://exmachina.in/28/09/2016/a-database-of-our-maladies/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/28/09/2016/a-database-of-our-maladies/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;India has the potential to use data innovatively for enhancing healthcare outcomes. However, it&amp;rsquo;s crucial to balance patient privacy with public good, defining clear grounds for data access and stringent punishments for misuse. The draft EHR legislation suggests patients &amp;ldquo;own&amp;rdquo; their medical data, but a nuanced approach focusing on access and control is needed. India has a unique opportunity to leverage technology for healthcare, but must strike the right balance between personal privacy and public good.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>