<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Ex Machina</title>
    <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Ex Machina</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 17:17:58 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://rahulmatthan.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Momentous Change</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/january/2023/momentous-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 17:17:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/january/2023/momentous-change/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We are potentially on the verge of momentous change. Artificial intelligence has improved to the point where it could pass as human. As a result, the search technology that was responsible for so much of the modern internet is facing its strongest challenge and with it the business model of the internet as we know it is under threat.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking Back</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/28/december/2022/looking-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 17:17:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/28/december/2022/looking-back/</guid>
      <description>In my very first article of the year I predicted that 2022 would be a busy year for tech policy. I was basing my prediction on the progress that had been made so far on our draft privacy law - the fact that now that the Joint Parliamentary Committee had finally submitted its draft, it seemed inevitable that the bill was well on its way to becoming a law. I saw the immediate next steps as being crucial - the establishment of the Data Protection Authority, the creation of rules, regulations and codes of practice and the daunting task of orienting commercial practice around a new culture of compliance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Idea Factories</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/december/2022/idea-factories/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2022 17:17:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/december/2022/idea-factories/</guid>
      <description>Over the course of my career, I have come across entrepreneurs of all hues.
Some are bubbling with inspiration, constantly finding solutions to the problems around them. They have an almost inexhaustible supply of ideas and the energy and inclination to worry away at a problem till they’ve figured out how to solve it. They love to mend what’s broken in the world—the problems no one else has been able to solve.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Truth and LLMs</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/14/december/2022/truth-and-llms/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2022 17:17:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/14/december/2022/truth-and-llms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If the purpose of education is to equip the younger generation with the skills they need to face the challenges of the world they are growing into, it is important to constantly re-evaluate the role that technology will play in that future. While we must not expect the skill of the past to continue to be useful we should guard against trusting technology blindly.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ethics of Automation</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/june/2016/ethics-of-automation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/june/2016/ethics-of-automation/</guid>
      <description>All of a sudden, so many of our appliances—televisions, coffee machines, bathroom scales, light bulbs—have grown smart and integrated themselves into an enormous hive-mind that miraculously keeps us fit, our home temperatures controlled and our lives organised. It seems we are on the threshold of a new age, but even at this early stage, the enormous strains that this fundamental technological shift will place on the world, are already becoming visible.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trusting the Sharing Economy</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/08/june/2016/trusting-the-sharing-economy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 17:17:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/08/june/2016/trusting-the-sharing-economy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On-demand services that comprise the sharing economy are superior to their real world counterparts because of the dual feedback system. Trust identity based on dual feedback loops could create the civilised commercial ecosystem that has always been the ultimate objective of putting in place a regulatory framework.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What the New Geospatial Bill Means for You</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/may/2016/what-the-new-geospatial-bill-means-for-you/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/may/2016/what-the-new-geospatial-bill-means-for-you/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The provisions of the proposed Geospatial Bill should be no surprise as these obligations have formed part of the map policy that has existed for a very long time. But thanks to the government&amp;rsquo;s approach of being outwardly strict in legislation but practically benevolent in enforcement our map ecosystem has flourished.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Stiff Backbone of the Aadhaar Act</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/24/march/2016/the-stiff-backbone-of-the-aadhaar-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 17:17:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/24/march/2016/the-stiff-backbone-of-the-aadhaar-act/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;While it is not without its flaws, the Aadhaar Act imposes some of the strongest fetters on government over-reach of any legislation in the country.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
