<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Business of Law on Ex Machina</title>
    <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/tags/business-of-law/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Business of Law on Ex Machina</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://rahulmatthan.github.io/tags/business-of-law/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Embracing ODR</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/24/01/2024/embracing-odr/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/24/01/2024/embracing-odr/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://rahulmatthan.github.io/images/courtroom-of-future.jpg&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The ODR approach can offer the soon-to-be-formed Data Protection Board mechanisms that are digital from the ground up. By integrating various elements of India’s digital public infrastructure into the ODR process adopted, we can ensure that data protection in India is techno-legal from the get-go.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lawyer, Disrupt Thyself</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/07/2022/lawyer-disrupt-thyself/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/07/2022/lawyer-disrupt-thyself/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We need technological disruption in India&amp;rsquo;s legal system. I believe this would reqire us to maximise the potential of online dispute resolution (ODR). The upcoming GST Appellate Tribunal could be a unique opportunity to leverage ODR, transforming the legal profession through efficiency and accessibility.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accessible Legal Systems</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/08/02/2022/accessible-legal-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/08/02/2022/accessible-legal-systems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Indian Supreme Court&amp;rsquo;s struggle to decipher a convoluted legal order highlights a broader issue of intentional incomprehensibility in legal language. This complexity often makes laws inaccessible to laypersons. We need plain language reforms, comprehensive lists of laws, explainers for every law, and measures to ease the compliance burdens if we are to make the legal systems more accessible and democratic.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Judicial Sector Reform</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/13/04/2021/judicial-sector-reform/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/13/04/2021/judicial-sector-reform/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In order to effect the judicial sector reforms that has been outlined in the Digital Courts Vision document, we need to unbundle the workflows in the judicial system and reduce them down to their constituent parts. We should then focus on the outcomes we are looking to achieve and re-assemble them using re-usable building blocks from existing stack infrastructure. Since much of the digitisation of the judicial sector can be expressed in terms of data flows we can achieve this by borrowing from the design of DEPA.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A golden opportunity to reform India’s judicial system</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/10/06/2020/a-golden-opportunity-to-reform-indias-judicial-system/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/10/06/2020/a-golden-opportunity-to-reform-indias-judicial-system/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Covid forced courts to adapt to remote working. And they did remarkably well considering the extent to which court processes rely on physical interactions. We need to use this opportunity to radically re-imagine dispute resolution. We can move to written advocacy, use artificial intelligence to make better decisions about litigation strategy - such as the chance of success of an appeal.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Online Dispute Resolution</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/09/06/2020/online-dispute-resolution/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/09/06/2020/online-dispute-resolution/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We need to radically reimaginine India&amp;rsquo;s justice delivery system by leveraging digital technology. We should propose written advocacy into the dispute resolution workflow and rely on data-driven reports to inform litigation strategies. How much we can transform is only limited by our courage.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Store data efficiently to get insights for justice reforms</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/10/2019/store-data-efficiently-to-get-insights-for-justice-reforms/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/10/2019/store-data-efficiently-to-get-insights-for-justice-reforms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Indian judicial system is in dire need of reform, with cases piling up and delays becoming a norm. While some digital information exists, the system remains largely analog, lacking crucial metrics and insights. Agami, an organization supporting legal innovation, is working to build a repository for legal data sets, aiming to develop a cloud storage system for collecting, storing, and updating legal data. This project is seen as a first step towards using data to understand and address the inefficiencies in the Indian legal system.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Adaptive legal advice for shape-shifting businesses</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/25/09/2019/adaptive-legal-advice-for-shape-shifting-businesses/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Sep 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/25/09/2019/adaptive-legal-advice-for-shape-shifting-businesses/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lawyers often struggle to advise innovative tech businesses due to their risk-averse, backward-looking training. They focus on legal risks, ignoring potential upsides. Modern businesses need lawyers who assess risks realistically, understand regulatory reactions, and advise based on future legal landscapes. Legal education needs a paradigm shift towards solution-focused, forward-thinking training.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ridding the judicial system of human subjectivity</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/23/01/2019/ridding-the-judicial-system-of-human-subjectivity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/23/01/2019/ridding-the-judicial-system-of-human-subjectivity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Algorithmic sentencing, using machine learning to assess recidivism risk, has demonstrated consistent outcomes. But is not without flaws, sometimes reflecting human biases. Despite imperfections, I believe algorithms can introduce objectivity and be fine-tuned to reduce biases, making them more reliable than human judgment.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disruption and innovation in the legal industry</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/08/2018/disruption-and-innovation-in-the-legal-industry/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 21 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/08/2018/disruption-and-innovation-in-the-legal-industry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Disruption always comes from where we least expect it. Lawyers exercise an iron grip over their profession. They determine who can practise law and how they should conduct their business. They organize themselves in bar councils that then determine how they can (and cannot) advertise and with whom they can share profits. If librarians had exerted the same sort of control over the organization of information as lawyers do over the business of the law, the modern internet might never have come to pass. Unless we lawyers can loosen the iron grip that we have over the business of law, the profession might never see the disruption that it needs and deserves.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The need for innovation in the legal sector</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/04/07/2018/the-need-for-innovation-in-the-legal-sector/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 04 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/04/07/2018/the-need-for-innovation-in-the-legal-sector/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is the nature of innovation that the ideas that gain traction are those that offer direct, tangible benefits to users. Since most legal technologies solve client problems they benefit clients more than the lawyers who use them. Legal technologies are slow ideas that will not disrupt the profession. We need fast, disruptive ideas and all that we are getting is incremental improvements in efficiency.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A game of Chinese whispers in the Aadhaar case</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/02/05/2018/a-game-of-chinese-whispers-in-the-aadhaar-case/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/02/05/2018/a-game-of-chinese-whispers-in-the-aadhaar-case/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There is a need for accurate, real-time court reporting by professional journalists. At present we are relying on lawyers&amp;rsquo; live tweets that cannot be expected to be unbiased and factual public information. We need to make changes to enable this institutionally.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Will technology be able to disrupt the legal industry?</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/03/2018/will-technology-be-able-to-disrupt-the-legal-industry/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/03/2018/will-technology-be-able-to-disrupt-the-legal-industry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Complexity is the friction of the legal system. We need to simplify the entire legal system - making it more accessible and less mysterious. The reason we have not been able to achieve this is because unlike all other industries, lawyers exercise 360-degree control over every facet of the legal industry and protect the profession from disruption.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Collaborative AI</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/15/03/2017/collaborative-ai/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/15/03/2017/collaborative-ai/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Law firms struggle with partner compensation models, balancing profit and collaboration. The &amp;ldquo;eat-what-you-kill&amp;rdquo; model, based on individual revenue generation, can lead to competition and reduced cooperation. In contrast, the lockstep system, rewarding tenure over performance, may not fully incentivize productivity. Similar challenges exist in finance, where hedge funds guard proprietary data. Numerai, an AI firm, addresses this by using homomorphic encryption and a public platform, allowing data scientists to contribute to a meta-model, democratizing data without compromising confidentiality, and rewarding contributions with bitcoin. This innovative approach could inspire similar solutions in the legal industry.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Demise of the Artisanal Lawyer</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/06/07/2016/the-demise-of-the-artisanal-lawyer/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/06/07/2016/the-demise-of-the-artisanal-lawyer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The University of Oxford&amp;rsquo;s study revealed that 47% of jobs today could be replaced by computers, including cognitive and evaluative roles. While lawyers have a low risk of displacement, paralegals and legal assistants face a 94% chance of being replaced. The rise of AI in law could disrupt traditional apprenticeship models and requires the legal industry to reorganize before technology claims their livelihood.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
