<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Climate Change on Ex Machina</title><link>https://exmachina.in/tags/climate-change/</link><description>Recent content in Climate Change on Ex Machina</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://exmachina.in/tags/climate-change/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Enhanced Geothermal</title><link>https://exmachina.in/23/04/2025/enhanced-geothermal/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/23/04/2025/enhanced-geothermal/</guid><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/enhanced-geothermal.jpg" width="auto"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If India is to achieve its data centre ambitions, it needs to find new sources of efficient power. While nuclear is a solution, it will take too long to come on stream. We need alternatives, and enhanced geothermal might just be it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>DPI Thinking for COP30</title><link>https://exmachina.in/02/04/2025/dpi-thinking-for-cop30/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Apr 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/02/04/2025/dpi-thinking-for-cop30/</guid><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/dpi-thinking-for-cop30.jpg" width="auto"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The climate consensus is rapidly unravelling. With the developing world consistently failing to make the level of commitment required to prevent global warming from exceeding 1.5 degrees above pre-industrial levels, we need to think differently about achieving sustainable development. Could we apply DPI Thinking to this problem?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Cost of Cold</title><link>https://exmachina.in/19/03/2025/the-cost-of-cold/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/19/03/2025/the-cost-of-cold/</guid><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/the-cost-of-cold.jpg" width="auto"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;All we need to do to address our food insecurity is learn to better preserve food after it has been harvested. However, the technology we rely on to do that comes at a great cost. We need to find an alternative approach - one that prevents spoilage without harming the environment.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>An Internet for energy</title><link>https://exmachina.in/19/02/2025/an-internet-for-energy/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/19/02/2025/an-internet-for-energy/</guid><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/an-internet-for-energy.jpg" width="auto"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There is an urgent need to re-design our energy grid to take better advantage of all that digital has to offer. A recent paper describes how we can add a digital layer to existing infrastructure and use this digital energy grid to unlock greater efficiencies. But in order to realise this goal we will need a shift in our regulatory mindset.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Virtual Power Plants</title><link>https://exmachina.in/21/02/2024/virtual-power-plants/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/21/02/2024/virtual-power-plants/</guid><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/vpp.jpg" width="auto"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Everyone says we need to embrace renewable energy to address the challenges of climate change. But integrating variable supplies of electricity into our current grid is easier said than done. One way to do that might be to virtualise our power plants.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Solar Geoengineering</title><link>https://exmachina.in/04/10/2023/solar-geoengineering/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/04/10/2023/solar-geoengineering/</guid><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/solar-geoengineering.png" width="auto"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With the number of extreme weather events that occurred in 2023, there is a new urgency around the need to find alternate and innovative solutions to the problem of climate change. One easy option is solar geo-engineering - that can be implemented by startups that raise donor funds to send up balloons carrying sulphates. That said this is not without its fair share of concerns. Not the least of which is uneven cooling and the impact on monsoon patterns in India.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Green Fuel</title><link>https://exmachina.in/25/10/2022/green-fuel/</link><pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/25/10/2022/green-fuel/</guid><description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/green-fuel.jpg" width="auto"&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ethanol, a fuel that emits 44%–52% less greenhouse gas than petrol, is presented as a viable step towards sustainability for India, a major sugar producer like Brazil. By adopting flex-fuel technology and ethanol production techniques, India could significantly reduce CO2 emissions without immediate radical changes to its energy infrastructure.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Setting the Standard</title><link>https://exmachina.in/26/04/2022/setting-the-standard/</link><pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/26/04/2022/setting-the-standard/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I support India&amp;rsquo;s new draft battery-swapping policy for electric vehicles, particularly since it promotes battery-as-a-service and emphasizes openness without being overly prescriptive. However, we should aspire to lead in developing standards that align with its market, leveraging its position as the world&amp;rsquo;s largest two-wheeler market, and its expertise in the EV sector, to assume global leadership in battery swapping standards.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The case for meat options that taste like the real thing</title><link>https://exmachina.in/23/10/2019/the-case-for-meat-options-that-taste-like-the-real-thing/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/23/10/2019/the-case-for-meat-options-that-taste-like-the-real-thing/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There is a significant environmental impact to livestock production. It accounts for 40% of global agricultural output and has significant greenhouse gas emissions. To meet global warming targets, a drastic dietary shift is needed. We need to explore meat substitutes like Impossible Foods&amp;rsquo; products, that are a promising and nearly indistinguishable alternative to traditional meat.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>Getting the Earth out of the Anthropocene period</title><link>https://exmachina.in/19/12/2018/getting-the-earth-out-of-the-anthropocene-period/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/19/12/2018/getting-the-earth-out-of-the-anthropocene-period/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For the past 12,000 years, Earth&amp;rsquo;s circular orbit has provided stable temperatures, fostering the Holocene era, crucial for human development and agriculture. This unique period of warmth, longer than previous interglacials, is threatened by human-induced climate change, with CO2 levels exceeding safe limits. The transition to the Anthropocene era, marked by significant human impact, necessitates urgent global action on sustainability and emissions reduction, as highlighted in recent international agreements and commitments by various US entities, despite federal resistance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item><item><title>The Great Manure Crisis of 1894</title><link>https://exmachina.in/20/04/2017/the-great-manure-crisis-of-1894/</link><pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/20/04/2017/the-great-manure-crisis-of-1894/</guid><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the 19th century, London faced the Great Manure Crisis, a seemingly insurmountable urban catastrophe. The advent of automobiles resolved the issue within a decade. Might we dare to imaging that the global pollution crisis, might have a similar, as yet unknown technological solutions?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description></item></channel></rss>