<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Climate Change on Ex Machina</title>
    <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/tags/climate-change/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Climate Change on Ex Machina</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://rahulmatthan.github.io/tags/climate-change/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Green Fuel</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/25/10/2022/green-fuel/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/25/10/2022/green-fuel/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Ethanol, a fuel that emits 44%–52% less greenhouse gas than petrol, is presented as a viable step towards sustainability for India, a major sugar producer like Brazil. By adopting flex-fuel technology and ethanol production techniques, India could significantly reduce CO2 emissions without immediate radical changes to its energy infrastructure.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Setting the Standard</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/26/04/2022/setting-the-standard/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Apr 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/26/04/2022/setting-the-standard/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I support India&amp;rsquo;s new draft battery-swapping policy for electric vehicles, particularly since it promotes battery-as-a-service and emphasizes openness without being overly prescriptive. However, we should aspire to lead in developing standards that align with its market, leveraging its position as the world&amp;rsquo;s largest two-wheeler market, and its expertise in the EV sector, to assume global leadership in battery swapping standards.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The case for meat options that taste like the real thing</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/23/10/2019/the-case-for-meat-options-that-taste-like-the-real-thing/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/23/10/2019/the-case-for-meat-options-that-taste-like-the-real-thing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There is a significant environmental impact to livestock production. It accounts for 40% of global agricultural output and has significant greenhouse gas emissions. To meet global warming targets, a drastic dietary shift is needed. We need to explore meat substitutes like Impossible Foods&amp;rsquo; products, that are a promising and nearly indistinguishable alternative to traditional meat.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Getting the Earth out of the Anthropocene period</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/19/12/2018/getting-the-earth-out-of-the-anthropocene-period/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/19/12/2018/getting-the-earth-out-of-the-anthropocene-period/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;For the past 12,000 years, Earth&amp;rsquo;s circular orbit has provided stable temperatures, fostering the Holocene era, crucial for human development and agriculture. This unique period of warmth, longer than previous interglacials, is threatened by human-induced climate change, with CO2 levels exceeding safe limits. The transition to the Anthropocene era, marked by significant human impact, necessitates urgent global action on sustainability and emissions reduction, as highlighted in recent international agreements and commitments by various US entities, despite federal resistance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Great Manure Crisis of 1894</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/20/04/2017/the-great-manure-crisis-of-1894/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 20 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/20/04/2017/the-great-manure-crisis-of-1894/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the 19th century, London faced the Great Manure Crisis, a seemingly insurmountable urban catastrophe. The advent of automobiles resolved the issue within a decade. Might we dare to imaging that the global pollution crisis, might have a similar, as yet unknown technological solutions?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
