<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Privacy on Ex Machina</title><link>https://exmachina.in/tags/privacy/</link><description>Recent content in Privacy on Ex Machina</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://exmachina.in/tags/privacy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>A 3-Step DPDP Compliance Guide</title><link>https://exmachina.in/19/11/2025/a-3-step-dpdp-compliance-guide/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Nov 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/19/11/2025/a-3-step-dpdp-compliance-guide/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/3-step-dpdp-compliance-guide.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>Now that we know the DPDP Act, 2023 will come into force in just under 18 months, data fiduciaries have begun to panic, worried that they have left it too late. For all the procrastinators out there, here is an easy 3-step guide to assessing where you currently stand.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Cognitive Liberty</title><link>https://exmachina.in/24/09/2025/cognitive-liberty/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/24/09/2025/cognitive-liberty/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/cognitive-liberty.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>As the technology to collect neural information directly from our brains starts to become commercially viable, we need to think deeply about the social and ethical implications of this. Apart from just data protection we may need a broader articulation of cognitive liberty.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Big Data Protection</title><link>https://exmachina.in/21/05/2025/big-data-protection/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 May 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/21/05/2025/big-data-protection/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/big-data-protection.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>Modern privacy law is based on principles of data protection that were first articulated in the 1970s. As a result, it is based on the idea that we should collect as little data as possible to safeguard personal privacy. In the age of AI and big data, that approach is fast losing its relevance.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Threading the Needle</title><link>https://exmachina.in/05/03/2025/threading-the-needle/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Mar 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/05/03/2025/threading-the-needle/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/threading-the-needle.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>Since data allows us to price risk more accurately and, at the same time allows us to offer incentives for appropriate behaviour, it is a very useful tool for insurers looking to achieve optimal risk pooling. However, if we take it too far we risk ending up in a surveillance society.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Consent Managers</title><link>https://exmachina.in/26/02/2025/consent-managers/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/26/02/2025/consent-managers/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/consent-managers.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>The introduction of the term Consent Manager in the Digital Personal Data Protection Act gave rise to considerable speculation. No other data protection law had anything like it, and the law itself was unclear as to what role these entities played. Now that the Rules are with us, things are a little clearer.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The DPDP Rules: First Impressions</title><link>https://exmachina.in/06/01/2025/the-dpdp-rules-first-impressions/</link><pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/06/01/2025/the-dpdp-rules-first-impressions/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/the-dpdp-rules-first-impressions.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>The much awaited Digital Personal Data Protection Rules are finally with us and, with that the final piece of the puzzle is in place. While there is a lot to unpack, overall, the Rules follow the Act in terms of simplicity - adding just enough to make it complete without complicating things unduly. That said, there are a few issues that still need to be sorted out.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Networked Privacy</title><link>https://exmachina.in/06/11/2024/networked-privacy/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Nov 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/06/11/2024/networked-privacy/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/networked-privacy.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>The individual agency that privacy laws offer were designed for a time before networked privacy. As a result we cannot just rely on laws and regulations to protect our data but need to do considerable additional work to secure it.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Acquiring Genetic Data</title><link>https://exmachina.in/16/10/2024/acquiring-genetic-data/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/16/10/2024/acquiring-genetic-data/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/acquiring-genetic-data.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>The question of what is to be done with personal data in the course of an M&amp;amp;A transaction is always complicated. It becomes even more so when the data in question is highly sensitive genetic information that was collected for a specific purpose. We need to think through these issues as the Indian law comes into force.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Homo Privaticus</title><link>https://exmachina.in/09/10/2024/homo-privaticus/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/09/10/2024/homo-privaticus/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/homo-privaticus.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>We have built our data protection laws on the edifice of consent. As a result, they are based on constructs that are derived from contractual frameworks. While this may have been acceptable in the early days of privacy law, the harms they need to protect against today are perhaps more effectively dealt with under tort law. We need to re-think consent.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Data Transfer Interoperability</title><link>https://exmachina.in/02/10/2024/data-transfer-interoperability/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Oct 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/02/10/2024/data-transfer-interoperability/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/data-transfer-interoperability.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>While data protection laws are, for the most part, domestically focussed, when personal data has to move across border they need to work well with each other. But before that can happen, countries need to agree on the principles of interoperability.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Are We Willing to Change</title><link>https://exmachina.in/17/07/2024/are-we-willing-to-change/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/17/07/2024/are-we-willing-to-change/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/are-we-willing-to-change.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>India&amp;rsquo;s new data protection law will require businesses to make significant changes to the ways in which they conduct their business. To the point where they will have to fundamentally re-imagine their ways of working. It is not clear to me that many of them understand the sheer magnitude of what that entails.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Age Tokens</title><link>https://exmachina.in/10/04/2024/age-tokens/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Apr 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/10/04/2024/age-tokens/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/age-tokens.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>One of the more worrisome provisions of India&amp;rsquo;s new data protection law has to do with processing of children&amp;rsquo;s data - and in particular, how data fiduciaries should go about verifying the age of those whose data they process. Thanks to India&amp;rsquo;s digital public infrastructure, I believe we may have a novel solution.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Embracing ODR</title><link>https://exmachina.in/24/01/2024/embracing-odr/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/24/01/2024/embracing-odr/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/courtroom-of-future.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>The ODR approach can offer the soon-to-be-formed Data Protection Board mechanisms that are digital from the ground up. By integrating various elements of India’s digital public infrastructure into the ODR process adopted, we can ensure that data protection in India is techno-legal from the get-go.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>We've Got Work To Do</title><link>https://exmachina.in/16/08/2023/weve-got-work-to-do/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/16/08/2023/weve-got-work-to-do/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/weve-got-work-to-do.png" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>The Digital Personal Data Protection Act, 2023 is not perfect. There are many things I would have liked to change. But it has been enacted and it is the law we’ve been given. It is time to stop the hand-wringing and get on with working with what we have.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Business End of the DPDP Act</title><link>https://exmachina.in/08/08/2023/the-business-end-of-the-dpdp-act/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/08/08/2023/the-business-end-of-the-dpdp-act/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/the-business-end-of-the-dpdp-act.png" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>India&amp;rsquo;s new data protection law is simple and principle based. But it will require companies big and small to make radical changes to the way they operate. And I don&amp;rsquo;t think businesses fully realise the changes they are going to have to make.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Around The Corner</title><link>https://exmachina.in/19/07/2023/around-the-corner/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/19/07/2023/around-the-corner/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/around-the-corner.png" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>The Digital Personal Data Protection Bill - that has been listed as one of the items for discussion in the Monsoon Session of Parliament - will, if enacted be a significant first step in the journey to a functional privacy regime. But there is still a lot to be done including issuing regulations and establishing the Data Protection Board.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Sharp Lines</title><link>https://exmachina.in/12/07/2023/sharp-lines/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/12/07/2023/sharp-lines/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/sharp-lines.png" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>Regulating the intersection of data protection and competition is hard. Dominant platforms can leverage user data to create monopolies, limit user choice and raise competition concerns. As India prepares its own data protection law, it should try and avoid regulatory overlaps and strike a balance between data protection and competition regulation.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Looking Back</title><link>https://exmachina.in/28/12/2022/looking-back/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/28/12/2022/looking-back/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/looking-back.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>A reflection on the tech policy developments in India during 2022. While my initial predictions about data protection laws and tech sector reforms didn&amp;rsquo;t unfold as expected, there have been positive strides in India&amp;rsquo;s digital public infrastructure, like the UPI payment system and Account Aggregator ecosystem. India&amp;rsquo;s upcoming G20 presidency could further spotlight its techno-legal approach to regulation.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Data Breach</title><link>https://exmachina.in/30/11/2022/data-breach/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/30/11/2022/data-breach/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/data-breach.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>India&amp;rsquo;s new draft data protection law mandates that data fiduciaries must notify affected individuals and the Data Protection Board of a breach, but it lacks specifics as to timelines or remedial actions. I worry that over-reporting minor incidents could lead to public desensitization, and would have preferred a more balanced approach that only requires notification of only the most high-risk breaches, similar to the European GDPR.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Exceptionally Simple</title><link>https://exmachina.in/24/11/2022/exceptionally-simple/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/24/11/2022/exceptionally-simple/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/exceptionally-simple.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>The new draft of India&amp;rsquo;s digital data protection bill is praised for its simplicity and relatability, although it has raised concerns for its lack of detail and government exemptions. The draft also misses key concepts like data portability and uses non-standard terminology.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Digital Personal Data Protection</title><link>https://exmachina.in/23/11/2022/digital-personal-data-protection/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/23/11/2022/digital-personal-data-protection/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/dpdp.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>The latest draft of India&amp;rsquo;s Digital Data Protection Bill, 2022, stands out for its simplicity and new concepts like &amp;ldquo;voluntary undertaking&amp;rdquo; and official recognition of &amp;ldquo;consent managers.&amp;rdquo; However, it omits features like data portability and the right to be forgotten. Critics argue the draft lacks safeguards and over-delegates legislative authority, particularly around the concept of &amp;ldquo;deemed consent.&amp;rdquo; But the principles-based approach it espouses could ensure agile and enduring data protection regulation.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Privacy Impact Assessment</title><link>https://exmachina.in/20/09/2022/privacy-impact-assessment/</link><pubDate>Tue, 20 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/20/09/2022/privacy-impact-assessment/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/pia.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>Given the Indian government&amp;rsquo;s increased use of technology, concerns around personal privacy necessitate the conduct of privacy impact assessments and the implementation of appropriate safeguards, such as a government privacy office, to balance the benefits of the technology with the potential harms to privacy.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Judge Made Laws</title><link>https://exmachina.in/28/06/2022/judge-made-laws/</link><pubDate>Tue, 28 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/28/06/2022/judge-made-laws/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The US Supreme Court&amp;rsquo;s decision in Dobbs v. Jackson Medical overturned Roe v. Wade, ending the guaranteed right to abortion since 1973. The ruling challenges decades of jurisprudence, threatens civil liberties, and impacts personal privacy. It also raises questions about the doctrine of stare decisis and the frailty of judge-made law.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Unreasonable Enforcement</title><link>https://exmachina.in/31/05/2022/unreasonable-enforcement/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/31/05/2022/unreasonable-enforcement/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>We need to have checks and balances in law enforcement, even though technological advancements will allow us to take shortcuts. Else we will not be able to prevent state overreach that affects the fundamental rights of citizens.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Light at the End of the Tunnel</title><link>https://exmachina.in/21/12/2021/light-at-the-end-of-the-tunnel/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/21/12/2021/light-at-the-end-of-the-tunnel/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>An analysis of the JPCs draft of the data protection bill has some welcome changes - the amendments to children&amp;rsquo;s data and the introduction of Section 62 that allows complaints to be filed. It also has some misguided changes such as the introduction of NGOs in the definitions. It also has changes that will have a significant impact such as the amendments to Section 35 and 36 on exemptions to law enforcement. Finally it introduces some new concepts that are problematic such as the requirement that data protection officers in companies need to be senior officials and the inclusion of non-personal data within the ambit of the law.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Privacy Self-Management</title><link>https://exmachina.in/11/11/2021/privacy-self-management/</link><pubDate>Thu, 11 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/11/11/2021/privacy-self-management/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>When there were limited uses to which data could be put, it was easy to evaluate the harms that could result from providing consent. Things are much more complex today so data protection regulations have tried to improve the quality of consent. This has resulted in the transparency paradox. If we can adopt consent templates we can give users appropriate autonomy.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Calculated Communication</title><link>https://exmachina.in/03/11/2021/calculated-communication/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/03/11/2021/calculated-communication/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Every evolution of communications technology from the printing press to the telegraph to telephones and eventually the internet has placed new and different stresses on personal privacy. As much as we welcome these technologies when launched, in time we realise the effect that they can have on personal privacy. The whole point of communicating is to violate your privacy in a controlled way. But if we do not have information about all the ways in which a given communication can affect your privacy you cannot really exercise effective control over it.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Identity and Privacy</title><link>https://exmachina.in/21/10/2021/identity-and-privacy/</link><pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/21/10/2021/identity-and-privacy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Identity is a prerequisite for the provision of services and efficient identity systems are necessary to scale digital public infrastructure. We can build back trust in identity systems through encryption and tokenisation of identity information by using privacy preserving technologies like zero knowledge proofs so that we can still establish eligibility for a service without exposing identity information.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Overlap</title><link>https://exmachina.in/30/03/2021/overlap/</link><pubDate>Tue, 30 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/30/03/2021/overlap/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Issues of privacy and competition often overlap and we need a coordinated approach between regulators. That works in the US and EU where both the privacy and the competition regulators are active. In India, where we are yet to establish a privacy regulator, the competition commission will step in and regulate privacy aspects of data businesses from a competition perspective. There is a risk that privacy will be decided from a competition perspective. We need a data protection authority asap.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Competition in Telecoms</title><link>https://exmachina.in/09/02/2021/competition-in-telecoms/</link><pubDate>Tue, 09 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/09/02/2021/competition-in-telecoms/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The Competition Commission of India has argued that since privacy is a non-price factor of competition, the competition regulator can regulate it. Privacy is a specialised area that should not be entrusted to a regulator that brings a purely economic lens its regulation.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Consent to Port</title><link>https://exmachina.in/08/09/2020/consent-to-port/</link><pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/08/09/2020/consent-to-port/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The Data Empowerment and Protection Architecture framework allows data companies to collect consent for data portability just before transfer, simplifying privacy policies and focusing them on data collection and use. This unbundling of consent improves user control over personal data and enhances privacy.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Data localization could soon be the worldwide reality</title><link>https://exmachina.in/29/07/2020/data-localization-could-soon-be-the-worldwide-reality/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/29/07/2020/data-localization-could-soon-be-the-worldwide-reality/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The European Court of Justice&amp;rsquo;s ruling on the US-EU Privacy Shield, impacts global data transfer practices. This decision, highlighting the importance of local laws in data protection, may lead to increased data localization, affecting countries like India and beyond, potentially restricting European data within Europe&amp;rsquo;s borders.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The untold story behind the evolution of privacy rights</title><link>https://exmachina.in/08/07/2020/the-untold-story-behind-the-evolution-of-privacy-rights/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/08/07/2020/the-untold-story-behind-the-evolution-of-privacy-rights/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The article &amp;ldquo;The Right to Privacy&amp;rdquo; by Samuel Warren and Louis Brandeis, published in 1890, has been influential in shaping modern privacy law. This foundational work has indirectly contributed to securing protections for the LGBTQ+ community, including influencing decisions that decriminalized homosexuality in the U.S. and India. But recent scholarship suggests that Warren&amp;rsquo;s motivation for writing the article may not have been what we thought it was.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Tech-enabled oversight could put innovation at threat</title><link>https://exmachina.in/06/05/2020/tech-enabled-oversight-could-put-innovation-at-threat/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/06/05/2020/tech-enabled-oversight-could-put-innovation-at-threat/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>When Mario Costeja Gonzales filed a complaint against Google in Spain, it lead to the creation of the &amp;ldquo;right to be forgotten.&amp;rdquo; Technology&amp;rsquo;s perfect memory challenges traditional legal concepts like bankruptcy law, which relies on human forgetfulness. We need to worry about technology-enhanced regulation, as it could stifle innovation and flexibility in business. We may need a new right to be forgotten in the context of regulation.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Jio-Facebook deal and our need for a privacy law</title><link>https://exmachina.in/29/04/2020/the-jio-facebook-deal-and-our-need-for-a-privacy-law/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/29/04/2020/the-jio-facebook-deal-and-our-need-for-a-privacy-law/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Facebook&amp;rsquo;s acquisition of a 9.99% stake in Jio Platforms has led to the integration of WhatsApp with JioMart, Reliance&amp;rsquo;s grocery platform. The collaboration&amp;rsquo;s scope and implementation remain unclear, but concerns arise regarding the impact on privacy - especially in the absence of a data protection law in India.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Mobility datasets could help India exit the lockdown</title><link>https://exmachina.in/22/04/2020/mobility-datasets-could-help-india-exit-the-lockdown/</link><pubDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/22/04/2020/mobility-datasets-could-help-india-exit-the-lockdown/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>During India&amp;rsquo;s fifth week of lockdown, measures have slowed COVID-19&amp;rsquo;s spread, despite testing and reporting concerns. A staggered lifting of restrictions is planned, balancing disease control with economic needs. Utilizing mobility data can guide reopening strategies, but privacy concerns must be addressed, especially in less dense areas.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The privacy features that are built into Aarogya Setu</title><link>https://exmachina.in/08/04/2020/the-privacy-features-that-are-built-into-aarogya-setu/</link><pubDate>Wed, 08 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/08/04/2020/the-privacy-features-that-are-built-into-aarogya-setu/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The Indian government&amp;rsquo;s Aarogya Setu app aims to slow the spread of COVID-19 by tracking and testing those who have come into contact with infected individuals. Despite concerns over personal privacy, the app incorporates privacy protections such as dissociating personal data, retaining data on the device by default, and strict data retention policies.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Liberties yielded in this crisis could set a new normal</title><link>https://exmachina.in/25/03/2020/liberties-yielded-in-this-crisis-could-set-a-new-normal/</link><pubDate>Wed, 25 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/25/03/2020/liberties-yielded-in-this-crisis-could-set-a-new-normal/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Post-9/11 and 26/11 attacks, security measures at US airports and Indian hotels became stringent, normalizing privacy sacrifices for safety. The COVID-19 crisis demands similar privacy compromises for health surveillance, potentially resetting our privacy expectations permanently, but we must resist normalizing this intrusion post-crisis.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The trade-off between privacy and content traceability</title><link>https://exmachina.in/26/02/2020/the-trade-off-between-privacy-and-content-traceability/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/26/02/2020/the-trade-off-between-privacy-and-content-traceability/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The use of end-to-end encryption is essential for privacy but also poses challenges, as it can be misused for criminal activities, such as the distribution of Child Sexual Abuse Imagery (CSAI). The paper presented at the Web Conference 2019 highlights the exponential growth in CSAI, correlating it with technological advancements. The dilemma lies in finding a balance between protecting civil liberties through encryption and preventing its exploitation for criminal purposes.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The trouble with using DNA matches to nab criminals</title><link>https://exmachina.in/04/12/2019/the-trouble-with-using-dna-matches-to-nab-criminals/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/04/12/2019/the-trouble-with-using-dna-matches-to-nab-criminals/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The arrest of the Golden State Killer, a serial criminal, was made possible through advances in DNA technology and commercial forensic genealogy. While effective in solving crimes, the use of public genetic information raises serious privacy concerns, potentially harming innocent relatives and uncovering unwanted private information.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A blueprint for an effective data protection authority</title><link>https://exmachina.in/20/11/2019/a-blueprint-for-an-effective-data-protection-authority/</link><pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/20/11/2019/a-blueprint-for-an-effective-data-protection-authority/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>India&amp;rsquo;s Data Protection Authority (DPA) must adopt technology to manage the high volume of privacy violation complaints and data-breach notifications. The DPA needs experts in technology, law, and privacy to balance privacy protection with technological innovation, requiring members beyond the traditional pool of bureaucrats and retired judges.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>We may need a whole new approach to data protection</title><link>https://exmachina.in/09/10/2019/we-may-need-a-whole-new-approach-to-data-protection/</link><pubDate>Wed, 09 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/09/10/2019/we-may-need-a-whole-new-approach-to-data-protection/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>There is a tension between data collectors and data subjects regarding ownership and value of their data. WHile traditional ownership concepts have not really succeeded when it comes to data regulation, contained within the idea of either collector-centric or subject-centric data trusts we might find an alternative approach to data governance.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>End-to-end encryption must be retained at all cost</title><link>https://exmachina.in/28/08/2019/end-to-end-encryption-must-be-retained-at-all-cost/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/28/08/2019/end-to-end-encryption-must-be-retained-at-all-cost/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Stripping away anonymity entirely from social media platforms will never ever be useful. Just because a few have taken advantage of online anonymity for nefarious purposes does not mean that everyone else should be denied the many benefits that technology platforms provide.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A new framework for consent to ensure data privacy</title><link>https://exmachina.in/07/08/2019/a-new-framework-for-consent-to-ensure-data-privacy/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/07/08/2019/a-new-framework-for-consent-to-ensure-data-privacy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The effectiveness of consent in protecting privacy is diminishing in our data-rich world. A study found that companies&amp;rsquo; privacy policies and actual data sharing practices are inconsistent, with technically sophisticated firms sharing less data. A digital consent framework, exemplified by India&amp;rsquo;s account aggregator system, could enhance privacy protection by allowing dynamic, informed consent, but it currently lacks features to fully ensure privacy, such as purpose limitation and data deletion upon consent revocation. Enhancements to this framework could restore faith in consent as a tool for privacy protection.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The needle in the digital haystack</title><link>https://exmachina.in/05/06/2019/the-needle-in-the-digital-haystack/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/05/06/2019/the-needle-in-the-digital-haystack/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Given the extensive surveillance efforts by the US and UK governments, as revealed by Edward Snowden, there has been a push for data localization laws in various countries. We need to question the effectiveness of mass data collection in preventing terrorism since the growing volume of data may render such efforts futile. At the same time we need to question the approach of data localization, given the difficulty in extracting actionable intelligence from vast amounts of information.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>How capitalism evolved to drop its defence of privacy</title><link>https://exmachina.in/24/04/2019/how-capitalism-evolved-to-drop-its-defence-of-privacy/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Apr 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/24/04/2019/how-capitalism-evolved-to-drop-its-defence-of-privacy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Historically, privacy was a luxury for the wealthy, who could afford private spaces and crafted distinct social personas. As society&amp;rsquo;s economic well-being improved, privacy became a societal expectation. Today, however, the rise of data-driven businesses threatens this privacy. Since privacy is rooted in capitalist interests, its preservation now conflicts with the commercial benefits of exploiting personal data. To protect privacy, we must establish commercial disincentives that outweigh the financial benefits of exploiting personal data.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Account aggregators and e-consent for credit markets</title><link>https://exmachina.in/30/01/2019/account-aggregators-and-e-consent-for-credit-markets/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/30/01/2019/account-aggregators-and-e-consent-for-credit-markets/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The public credit registry (PCR), a centralized credit information system, would improve data quality and help borrowers build reputational collateral. However, a PCR alone isn&amp;rsquo;t sufficient; lenders also need information on borrowers&amp;rsquo; financial assets. The Reserve Bank of India&amp;rsquo;s account aggregator infrastructure addresses this by allowing borrowers to share financial asset information securely and with consent. While this system limits data misuse, it requires robust legal frameworks to ensure data is used only for intended purposes.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The utter meaninglessness of anonymizing telecom data sets</title><link>https://exmachina.in/02/01/2019/the-utter-meaninglessness-of-anonymizing-telecom-data-sets/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/02/01/2019/the-utter-meaninglessness-of-anonymizing-telecom-data-sets/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Mobile phones provide opportunities to obtain real-time movement information, aiding in crisis management like tracking disease spread. However, the balance between utilizing this data and ensuring privacy is complex. Current anonymization methods are inadequate, and conscientious use obligations may be a more effective approach to protect privacy.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>When privacy, the word of the year, came into its own</title><link>https://exmachina.in/26/12/2018/when-privacy-the-word-of-the-year-came-into-its-own/</link><pubDate>Wed, 26 Dec 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/26/12/2018/when-privacy-the-word-of-the-year-came-into-its-own/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>This year marked a significant shift in global privacy regulation, with the enforcement of Europe&amp;rsquo;s GDPR and similar laws in other regions. While focusing on consent, the inadequacy of this approach was exposed by tech companies&amp;rsquo; practices. In India, the privacy debate intensified with court decisions on Aadhaar and the release of the Justice Srikrishna Committee&amp;rsquo;s draft bill.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Restoring the original vision of the internet</title><link>https://exmachina.in/10/10/2018/restoring-the-original-vision-of-the-internet/</link><pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/10/10/2018/restoring-the-original-vision-of-the-internet/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The modern internet has become centralized and controlled by a few powerful corporations, deviating from its original vision of an open and decentralized platform. Tim Berners-Lee, the founding father of the internet, is working on a project called Solid to restore power to users by allowing them to store personal information in personal data stores (PDS) under their control. That said, universally accepted standards for electronic consent and true social graph portability might be a more effective way to balance convenience and data protection.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Aadhaar verdict: everybody lost</title><link>https://exmachina.in/03/10/2018/the-aadhaar-verdict-everybody-lost/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/03/10/2018/the-aadhaar-verdict-everybody-lost/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The recent Supreme Court judgment on Aadhaar has left confusion and dissatisfaction among various stakeholders. While the court upheld the identity scheme, it restricted its scope, leading to uncertainty over the role of the private sector in Aadhaar&amp;rsquo;s infrastructure. The judgment&amp;rsquo;s implications on government services and subsidies, many of which rely on private sector authentication, remain unclear, raising concerns about potential negative impacts on pensioners, migrant workers, and microfinance beneficiaries.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>When parents damage their children’s digital privacy</title><link>https://exmachina.in/12/09/2018/when-parents-damage-their-childrens-digital-privacy/</link><pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/12/09/2018/when-parents-damage-their-childrens-digital-privacy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The draft Personal Data Protection Bill in India aims to protect children&amp;rsquo;s online privacy through age verification and parental consent. However, these measures raise concerns about the loss of internet anonymity and practical issues with the age threshold. The Bill&amp;rsquo;s approach may inadvertently expose children to privacy risks, including those stemming from well-intentioned parental actions, and fails to consider children&amp;rsquo;s ability to make decisions about their privacy before reaching the age of majority.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Limiting the government’s ability to violate privacy</title><link>https://exmachina.in/18/08/2018/limiting-the-governments-ability-to-violate-privacy/</link><pubDate>Sat, 18 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/18/08/2018/limiting-the-governments-ability-to-violate-privacy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Justice Brandeis&amp;rsquo; dissent in the matter of Roy Olmstead, emphasises the dangers of unchecked government surveillance and the need for privacy laws to evolve with technology, remains highly relevant, especially in discussions about government exemptions in privacy laws and the balance between using technology for social good and protecting civil liberties.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Balancing Big Data and privacy</title><link>https://exmachina.in/01/08/2018/balancing-big-data-and-privacy/</link><pubDate>Wed, 01 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/01/08/2018/balancing-big-data-and-privacy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The Justice Srikrishna Committee&amp;rsquo;s data protection framework aims to balance individual privacy with the growth of the digital economy, distinct from models in the US, EU, and China. But the committee missed opportunities to encourage de-identified data use and set impractical standards for anonymization. Concerns arise from the draft law&amp;rsquo;s definition of harm, potentially hindering AI and machine learning applications in social contexts by categorizing service denial based on evaluative decisions as harmful, which could restrict beneficial financial and social inclusion technologies.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Achilles heel of the draft personal data Bill</title><link>https://exmachina.in/31/07/2018/the-achilles-heel-of-the-draft-personal-data-bill/</link><pubDate>Tue, 31 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/31/07/2018/the-achilles-heel-of-the-draft-personal-data-bill/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The Srikrishna Committee report on India&amp;rsquo;s new privacy framework has been criticized for seemingly granting the government latitude in state surveillance, including national security exemptions. While similar exemptions are common in global data protection laws, concerns arise from the report&amp;rsquo;s failure to address practical concerns and the draft Bill&amp;rsquo;s inability to hold the government accountable for privacy violations. The penalties, designed with private entities in mind, may leave government data fiduciaries without fear of consequence.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Complexity will be the privacy law’s undoing</title><link>https://exmachina.in/30/07/2018/complexity-will-be-the-privacy-laws-undoing/</link><pubDate>Mon, 30 Jul 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/30/07/2018/complexity-will-be-the-privacy-laws-undoing/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The Justice Srikrishna Committee&amp;rsquo;s report on data protection proposes a user-centric framework, emphasizing data portability and privacy by design. However, its approach to consent, applying product liability principles and creating a complex, multilayered consent framework, may be impractical and burdensome for businesses, particularly startups. These measures, while aiming to enhance privacy, could introduce additional friction for users and businesses, potentially exacerbating consent fatigue.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>India should make clear laws on data collection</title><link>https://exmachina.in/27/06/2018/india-should-make-clear-laws-on-data-collection/</link><pubDate>Wed, 27 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/27/06/2018/india-should-make-clear-laws-on-data-collection/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The US Supreme Court recemtly ruled that collecting cellphone location data without a warrant violated privacy. This case challenges the third-party doctrine, which states that shared personal information has reduced privacy expectations. The ruling highlights the difficulty of applying traditional legal principles to modern technology, particularly regarding data privacy. This case could guide Indian privacy law, emphasizing the need for clear legislative direction on data collection and privacy.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The unintended consequences of Europe’s GDPR</title><link>https://exmachina.in/06/06/2018/the-unintended-consequences-of-europes-gdpr/</link><pubDate>Wed, 06 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/06/06/2018/the-unintended-consequences-of-europes-gdpr/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The General Data Protection Regulation (GDPR) came into force on 25 May, affecting entities worldwide that do business with EU citizens. While the regulation has stringent requirements for consent and high penalties for non-compliance, it may have unintended consequences. Large platforms can easily adapt, but smaller entities and start-ups may struggle with the complexity and cost of compliance, potentially leading to a consolidation towards large data platforms and a chilling effect on new ventures.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A new direction for data privacy in healthcare</title><link>https://exmachina.in/11/04/2018/a-new-direction-for-data-privacy-in-healthcare/</link><pubDate>Wed, 11 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/11/04/2018/a-new-direction-for-data-privacy-in-healthcare/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The draft Digital Information Security in Healthcare Act aims to regulate the use of digital health data, emphasizing patient consent and privacy. It allows anonymized data for public health research but restricts commercial use. However, its timing is questionable, as it precedes the anticipated overarching national data protection framework, potentially leading to inconsistencies in privacy regulations across sectors.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>India need not adopt the onerous European General Data Protection Regulation</title><link>https://exmachina.in/04/04/2018/india-need-not-adopt-the-onerous-european-general-data-protection-regulation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 04 Apr 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/04/04/2018/india-need-not-adopt-the-onerous-european-general-data-protection-regulation/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>There is no need for India to adopt GDPR-like data protection laws as it will hinder local innovation. Historically speaking countries took their time to arrive at a standardised approach to IP law and we need to follow a similar approach - taking a tailored approach to data regulation that balances protection with fostering its burgeoning data industry.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Do away with consent to strengthen data privacy</title><link>https://exmachina.in/28/03/2018/do-away-with-consent-to-strengthen-data-privacy/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Mar 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/28/03/2018/do-away-with-consent-to-strengthen-data-privacy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>That consent to the Facebook privacy policy could be used as a defence against the consequences of the Cambridge Analytica incident is an indication that consent cannot be our primary safeguard. The accountability framework is the only effective alternative to consent.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Data subject first</title><link>https://exmachina.in/13/12/2017/data-subject-first/</link><pubDate>Wed, 13 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/13/12/2017/data-subject-first/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>In early 1800s America, credit was based on personal familiarity. Lewis Tappan revolutionized this by selling credit ratings, leading to the birth of credit reporting agencies. Today, these agencies hold extensive personal data, influencing major life decisions. India, formulating its first privacy legislation, faces a similar choice: regulate data collectors or empower individuals to control their data usage.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Privacy and household finance</title><link>https://exmachina.in/30/08/2017/privacy-and-household-finance/</link><pubDate>Wed, 30 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/30/08/2017/privacy-and-household-finance/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The RBI Committee on Household Finance recommends the use of fintech to build the customisable, scalable solutions we need to benefit households.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Good and the Bad of the Privacy Ruling</title><link>https://exmachina.in/26/08/2017/the-good-and-the-bad-of-the-privacy-ruling/</link><pubDate>Sat, 26 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/26/08/2017/the-good-and-the-bad-of-the-privacy-ruling/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The Supreme Court of India&amp;rsquo;s decision in Puttuswamy v. Union of India affirmed the fundamental right to privacy, resolving inconsistencies in previous rulings. While the judgment is celebrated for its nuance, I am concerned that the consent-based framework might hinder the benefits of modern technology.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A New Hope for Personal Privacy</title><link>https://exmachina.in/12/08/2017/a-new-hope-for-personal-privacy/</link><pubDate>Sat, 12 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/12/08/2017/a-new-hope-for-personal-privacy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>We rely on technology for daily tasks - from timely reminders to personalized entertainment suggestions. While this personalization offers convenience and informed decision-making, it raises privacy concerns. The proposed privacy law shifts responsibility from individual consent to data controllers, ensuring no harm from data processing. This includes financial, reputational, or choice-related harms, especially from biased machine learning algorithms. The law suggests regular data audits by learned intermediaries, moving towards privacy compliance through incentives rather than penalties.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Aadhaar: The Fine Balance between Identity and Anonymity</title><link>https://exmachina.in/17/05/2017/aadhaar-the-fine-balance-between-identity-and-anonymity/</link><pubDate>Wed, 17 May 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/17/05/2017/aadhaar-the-fine-balance-between-identity-and-anonymity/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>In &amp;ldquo;Homo Deus&amp;rdquo;, Yuval Noah Harari suggests that Homo sapiens&amp;rsquo; success is due to our unique ability to believe in myths, like nation-states, which unite individuals under a common identity. This concept is crucial in modern society, where identity systems like India&amp;rsquo;s Aadhaar balance social responsibilities with personal privacy, highlighting the need for privacy laws to maintain this equilibrium.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A New Paradigm for Privacy</title><link>https://exmachina.in/29/03/2017/a-new-paradigm-for-privacy/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/29/03/2017/a-new-paradigm-for-privacy/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The Indian government&amp;rsquo;s recent mandate to link Aadhaar numbers with tax returns and mobile numbers highlights the urgent need for a privacy law. Current proposals suggest a law based on OECD principles, emphasizing consent. However, given the complexity of data use today, the responsibility should shift from individual consent to holding data controllers accountable, ensuring fair and non-discriminatory data processing. India has the chance to create a forward-thinking privacy framework suitable for today&amp;rsquo;s data-intensive world.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Digital Inclusion for the 85%</title><link>https://exmachina.in/28/12/2016/digital-inclusion-for-the-85/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/28/12/2016/digital-inclusion-for-the-85/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>2016 was a transformative year, marked by the e-commerce sector&amp;rsquo;s challenges following the Indian government&amp;rsquo;s Press Note 3. This led to innovative business models and growth in related industries like logistics and warehousing. The year also saw Aadhaar enrolment surpass 1 billion, laying the foundation for India&amp;rsquo;s digital transformation. The introduction of India Stack, particularly the Unified Payment Interface (UPI), revolutionized digital payments. However, the focus shifted towards including the larger, underserved population in the digital economy, highlighting the need for a balanced policy framework that respects privacy while leveraging data-driven decision-making.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Its Time for Coveillance</title><link>https://exmachina.in/16/11/2016/its-time-for-coveillance/</link><pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/16/11/2016/its-time-for-coveillance/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Privacy is an aberration from the mutual surveillance (coveillance) society that we have always been a part of. With greater tensions being felt between new technologies and the need for greater privacy the solution is to embrace covaillance so that we can reduce the information asymmetry between the watcher and the watched.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Quantified Self</title><link>https://exmachina.in/19/10/2016/quantified-self/</link><pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/19/10/2016/quantified-self/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Wearable devices are increasingly common, tracking various physical activities and even finding their way into legal evidence. The future of medicine may lie in this quantified personal measurement, allowing for customized treatment tailored to individual patients. However, to reach this future, changes to regulatory frameworks and a rethinking of privacy notions are needed to allow for more patient-centric medical treatment and algorithmic diagnosis.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>A Database of our Maladies</title><link>https://exmachina.in/28/09/2016/a-database-of-our-maladies/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/28/09/2016/a-database-of-our-maladies/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>India has the potential to use data innovatively for enhancing healthcare outcomes. However, it&amp;rsquo;s crucial to balance patient privacy with public good, defining clear grounds for data access and stringent punishments for misuse. The draft EHR legislation suggests patients &amp;ldquo;own&amp;rdquo; their medical data, but a nuanced approach focusing on access and control is needed. India has a unique opportunity to leverage technology for healthcare, but must strike the right balance between personal privacy and public good.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The accountability framework</title><link>https://exmachina.in/29/06/2016/the-accountability-framework/</link><pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/29/06/2016/the-accountability-framework/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The consent-based model of data protection is outdated and ineffective in the modern, interconnected world. We need to shift from focusing on obtaining consent to holding organizations accountable for the data they control. India, lacking a formal privacy law, has a unique opportunity to develop a modern privacy law centered on accountability, which could serve as a model for the rest of the world.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Stiff Backbone of the Aadhaar Bill</title><link>https://exmachina.in/24/03/2016/the-stiff-backbone-of-the-aadhaar-bill/</link><pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>https://exmachina.in/24/03/2016/the-stiff-backbone-of-the-aadhaar-bill/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="https://exmachina.in/images/stiff-backbone-of-aadhaar.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>While it is not without its flaws, a closer examination of the provisions of the Aadhaar Act will make it clear that it imposes on the government, some of the strongest fetters on executive over-reach of any legislation in the country.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>