<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Regulation on Ex Machina</title>
    <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/tags/regulation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Regulation on Ex Machina</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://rahulmatthan.github.io/tags/regulation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Monopoly Over Dematerialised Violence</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/06/03/2024/monopoly-over-dematerialised-violence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Mar 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/06/03/2024/monopoly-over-dematerialised-violence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://rahulmatthan.github.io/images/exploding.jpg&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Advances in technology have transformed our societal interactions in ways that challenge the state&amp;rsquo;s monopoly over violence. Today large tech companies (not governments) determine how our interactions take place. Which means that we need to rethink governance structures if the state is to continue to protect its citizens.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pandora&#39;s Box</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/01/11/2023/pandoras-box/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Nov 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/01/11/2023/pandoras-box/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://rahulmatthan.github.io/images/pandoras-box.png&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The myth of Pandora&amp;rsquo;s box, where opening a forbidden container unleashed the world&amp;rsquo;s evils but also hope, parallels scientific discovery. Each breakthrough, like CRISPR&amp;rsquo;s medical potential, brings unforeseen challenges, as seen with its controversial use in gene editing. Technologies intended for good, like the internet or drones, can be subverted for harm. Regulation alone can&amp;rsquo;t contain such knowledge; instead, we must design incentives to align technology use with societal goals, preparing us to handle the inevitable consequences of human curiosity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A New Delhi Effect</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/25/10/2023/a-new-delhi-effect/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Oct 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/25/10/2023/a-new-delhi-effect/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://rahulmatthan.github.io/images/a-new-delhi-effect.png&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The &amp;ldquo;Brussels Effect&amp;rdquo; is the phenomenon where other countries adopt regulation similar to the EU&amp;rsquo;s and as a result ends up extending Europe&amp;rsquo;s regulatory dominance. However, regulations like the GDPR have faced criticism for its burdensome compliance requirements. India&amp;rsquo;s DPI approach offers a new data governance model. But in order for this approach to be globally successful, strong regulatory institutions and a commitment to techno-legal governance are necessary.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Around The Corner</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/19/07/2023/around-the-corner/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Jul 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/19/07/2023/around-the-corner/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://rahulmatthan.github.io/images/around-the-corner.png&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Digital Personal Data Protection Bill - that has been listed as one of the items for discussion in the Monsoon Session of Parliament - will, if enacted be a significant first step in the journey to a functional privacy regime. But there is still a lot to be done including issuing regulations and establishing the Data Protection Board.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>New Electronic Records</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/11/10/2022/new-electronic-records/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Oct 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/11/10/2022/new-electronic-records/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Information Technology Act, 2000 governs cyber incidents and data protection in India. A recent amendment permits certain negotiable instruments and real estate contracts to be executed digitally. Though narrow in scope, this change could significantly impact the financial and real estate sectors, fostering innovation and modernization.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Pre-Legislative Consultation</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/07/06/2022/pre-legislative-consultation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/07/06/2022/pre-legislative-consultation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In 2014, India’s ministry of law and justice issued a policy on pre-legislative consultation, partially drawing on OECD recommendations. While most legislative proposals in India set aside time for public comments, the consultation often appears to be a formality. We need to redesign the process so that stakeholders can approach the process constructively - recognizing that policy-making is a compromise, and that both government and stakeholders must be open to differing viewpoints.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Breach Notifications</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/10/05/2022/data-breach-notifications/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 10 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/10/05/2022/data-breach-notifications/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In India, the absence of comprehensive privacy law has led to over-reliance on CERT-In Rules, 2013, for data breach guidance. Recent directions by the Ministry of Electronics and Information Technology has expanded mandatory reporting requirements, raising concerns about inundating CERT-In with trivial incidents and, as a result, hindering its ability to respond to serious breaches.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Smart Regulation</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/15/12/2021/smart-regulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/15/12/2021/smart-regulation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There is a growing recognition of the fact that we can use technology tools to make our regulations smarter. There are 2 categories of tools to do this. The first gives users more control over what can be done with their data by placing data in pods and only allowing them to be accessed in accordance with the privacy management protocols. The second unlocks data silos allowing data to move between them with the consent of the user. While these tools seem contradictory they operate at opposite ends of the data spectrum can can be combined to augment statutory frameworks.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Striking a Balance</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/01/09/2021/striking-a-balance/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/01/09/2021/striking-a-balance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Policy-making requires an understanding of the reciprocal relationships inherent in regulation. Focusing on a policy outcome in a narrow area of specific intent will result in unintended consequences in reciprocally related areas. In these instances it is important to think about policy making as a dial. Tilting too much in one direction will cause harm elsewhere. It is about finding the right balance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Breaking the Rules</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/07/07/2021/breaking-the-rules/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Jul 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/07/07/2021/breaking-the-rules/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The pandemic forced us into a natural experiment that has given us valuable insights about the natural world in the absence of humans. It also allowed us to experiment with changing various regulations to continue to operate in a lockdown. We should use the learnings from this natural experiment to figure out how to implement empirical policy-making by implementing regulatory sandboxes for our policy endeavours.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Principle Based Regulations</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/02/02/2021/principle-based-regulations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/02/02/2021/principle-based-regulations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Regulation can never keep up with technology. What we need to do is develop principles-based regulation and allow regulators discretion in its implementation through effective post-facto enforcement. We should presume that regulatory actions have been taken in good faith unless proven otherwise and build transparency into our systems to ensure that regulators do not exceed their authority. Regulators should list all applicable regulations on their website and not attempt to enforce anything outside those regulations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Electronic Evidence</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/27/01/2021/electronic-evidence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/27/01/2021/electronic-evidence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In India, electronic records can only be brought into evidence if accompanied by a certificate signed by a responsible person describing how it was produced and details of the computer involved in its production. Unless we remove these offline measures and replace them with digital certificates and other forms of electronic authentication, digital dispute resolution will be crippled.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Retrospective</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/30/12/2020/retrospective/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 30 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/30/12/2020/retrospective/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;My reflections on my 2020 predictions about technological advancements. The pandemic emphasized technology&amp;rsquo;s central role in society, from remote working to vaccine development. New regulatory measures give hope for increased internet access and technology legislation in India, recognizing the need to adapt and engage with technology in new ways.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Bright Side of Life</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/25/11/2020/the-bright-side-of-life/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/25/11/2020/the-bright-side-of-life/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Despite our pessimistic focus on disasters and negative events, the world has significantly improved in areas like forced labor, women&amp;rsquo;s voting rights, literacy, and environmental protection. Even in tech policy and government handling of data privacy, progress is evident, though challenges remain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Platform Regulation</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/14/10/2020/platform-regulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/14/10/2020/platform-regulation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Different platforms require tailored regulations, and so operating systems and app stores should be regulated differently. Given the recent developments in India, where startups have challenged Google&amp;rsquo;s Play Store policy,  there is a need for innovative thinking beyond traditional regulatory solutions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Agile Tech Regulations</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/22/09/2020/agile-tech-regulations/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/22/09/2020/agile-tech-regulations/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If we are to take a comprehensive approach to tech sector regulation, we need to identify core regulatory objectives, establish regulatory principles, and involving experts in the regulatory process. We need agile governance that encourages multi-stakeholder participation, and allows for the creation of self-regulatory organizations (SROs). We should also establish technical standards organizations (TSOs) to continuously update and maintain digital public infrastructure standards, ensuring their relevance and effectiveness in the rapidly changing tech landscape.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The future is here. It is just not evenly distributed yet</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/01/01/2020/the-future-is-here.-it-is-just-not-evenly-distributed-yet/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/01/01/2020/the-future-is-here.-it-is-just-not-evenly-distributed-yet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technological advancements can have a transformative impact. This includes deep neural networks, augmented reality, autonomous transportation, and personalized medicine. I predicts a future where technology will become more intuitive, education will be revolutionized, personal vehicle ownership may decline, and medicine will become highly individualized, though regulators may lag behind these changes.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>We must guard against the casual disregard of science</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/11/12/2019/we-must-guard-against-the-casual-disregard-of-science/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/11/12/2019/we-must-guard-against-the-casual-disregard-of-science/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Trofim Lysenko&amp;rsquo;s misguided agricultural practices led to famines in the Soviet Union and China, killing millions. This is no different from the modern-day denial of climate science. We need to learn from the past and try not to ignore scientific evidence for political or economic reasons. Else we risk devastating global consequences.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A blueprint for an effective data protection authority</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/20/11/2019/a-blueprint-for-an-effective-data-protection-authority/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/20/11/2019/a-blueprint-for-an-effective-data-protection-authority/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;India&amp;rsquo;s Data Protection Authority (DPA) must adopt technology to manage the high volume of privacy violation complaints and data-breach notifications. The DPA needs experts in technology, law, and privacy to balance privacy protection with technological innovation, requiring members beyond the traditional pool of bureaucrats and retired judges.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A three-point plan to improve tech policy formulation</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/17/07/2019/a-three-point-plan-to-improve-tech-policy-formulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Jul 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/17/07/2019/a-three-point-plan-to-improve-tech-policy-formulation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Regulating technology is challenging due to its rapid evolution, leading to a disjointed patchwork of rules. Governments often react to technology&amp;rsquo;s harmful impacts rather than proactively anticipating them. Regulatory entrepreneurship, where changing laws is part of the business strategy, complicates this further. To improve technology regulation, the government should focus on real objectives, adopt principle-based laws, and seek expertise from various fields. This approach would ensure more effective, adaptable, and comprehensive technology regulation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Policy advocacy is really an exercise in compromise</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/06/02/2019/policy-advocacy-is-really-an-exercise-in-compromise/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/06/02/2019/policy-advocacy-is-really-an-exercise-in-compromise/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Despite a 2014 initiative by the ministry of law and justice that mandated pre-legislative consultation, in most instances the process is largely superficial. We need a more genuine and constructive engagement from both the government and stakeholders, emphasizing compromise and understanding. The government should actively facilitate pre-legislative consultation, evaluate competing suggestions, and align decisions with democratic values to ensure more meaningful participation in policy-making.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Time to redo FDI in e-commerce in India</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/01/2019/time-to-redo-fdi-in-e-commerce-in-india/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/01/2019/time-to-redo-fdi-in-e-commerce-in-india/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;India&amp;rsquo;s restriction on foreign investment in retail, extended to e-commerce, led to complex structures to navigate the limitation. The government&amp;rsquo;s recent regulations, instead of simplifying the policy, have endorsed the marketplace model, potentially leading to ongoing convoluted practices that may hinder consumer benefits and business ease.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Highway Ban</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/07/2017/the-highway-ban/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Jul 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/07/2017/the-highway-ban/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Supreme Court of India&amp;rsquo;s ban on liquor sales along highways led to the closure of bars and pubs on Bengaluru&amp;rsquo;s MG Road and Brigade Road, mistakenly identified as part of NH-4 and NH-7. The excise department&amp;rsquo;s order, based on outdated map information, ignored the city&amp;rsquo;s changed highway network, reflecting a broader issue with government map coordination. The Supreme Court later clarified that the ban should not&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Path Dependence</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/14/06/2017/path-dependence/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/14/06/2017/path-dependence/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The QWERTY keyboard layout was designed to slow down typing to prevent mechanical jams. This design has persisted despite alternatives that could improve typing speeds. Path dependence like this is reflected in the legislative process in India, where outdated laws still govern modern technology. We need to break free from path dependence, especially in the context of enacting a new privacy law, to create regulations that are responsive to modern technology.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FOMO and the Law</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/01/03/2017/fomo-and-the-law/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 01 Mar 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/01/03/2017/fomo-and-the-law/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Lawmaking, fraught with the challenge of foreseeing unintended consequences, often leads to statutes filled with broad, catch-all provisions. These residuary clauses, while providing regulatory flexibility, create uncertainty and potential for overreach. The Other Service Providers (OSPs) regulations in telecom exemplify this, with vague definitions extending regulatory reach to unintended sectors. Precise, purpose-built legislation is advocated over open-ended definitions to avoid such regulatory ambiguities.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regulatory Sandbox</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/25/01/2017/regulatory-sandbox/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/25/01/2017/regulatory-sandbox/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Indian government&amp;rsquo;s approach to using imprecise language in law-making - particularly in technology regulation - can lead to unintended consequences. If we can use regulatory &amp;ldquo;sandboxes&amp;rdquo; to safely test new technologies to be tested within controlled environments it would foster innovation and create more precise and effective regulations.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regtech Will Change the Way We Regulate</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/26/10/2016/regtech-will-change-the-way-we-regulate/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/26/10/2016/regtech-will-change-the-way-we-regulate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Since the 2008 financial crisis, increased regulatory measures have led to higher compliance costs for financial institutions. Many banks&amp;rsquo; legacy systems are struggling with these demands. Emerging RegTech start-ups are addressing this by using modern cloud-based technologies to simplify compliance. This field promises to transform regulation through efficient data processing, real-time API-driven compliance, and a shift from prescriptive legislation to principle-based algorithms.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lazy Legislation</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/10/08/2016/lazy-legislation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/10/08/2016/lazy-legislation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;While Press Note 3 of 2016, was supposed to liberalise FDI in e-commerce in India, it is filled with contradictory provisions and unclear definitions - particularly regarding the inclusion of service and digital product sales in e-commerce. It is, in fact, a step back and is reflective of the fact that the government&amp;rsquo;s understanding of technology and its impact is inadequate. Effective regulation in the Network Age requires precise, flexible legislation, understanding network patterns, and a non-linear approach to policy formulation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Tech to Ensure Data Symmetry</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/27/07/2016/using-tech-to-ensure-data-symmetry/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/27/07/2016/using-tech-to-ensure-data-symmetry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Internet and modern technologies have reduced information asymmetry in markets. With the abundance of data available today, can technology can replace regulations, ensuring data symmetry and achieving &amp;ldquo;minimum governance?&amp;rdquo;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
