<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Innovation on Ex Machina</title><link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/tags/innovation/</link><description>Recent content in Innovation on Ex Machina</description><generator>Hugo</generator><language>en</language><lastBuildDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://rahulmatthan.github.io/tags/innovation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><item><title>Synthetic Biology</title><link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/28/08/2024/synthetic-biology/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/28/08/2024/synthetic-biology/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="http://rahulmatthan.github.io/images/synthetic-biology.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>While synthetic biology offers us many significant benefits, there is a risk that these benefits will accrue to the wealthy nations and corporations that currently control almost all cutting edge research in the field. To secure our interests we need to participate in global discussions on the subject. And increase our investments in the sector.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Open AI Innovation</title><link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/31/07/2024/open-ai-innovation/</link><pubDate>Wed, 31 Jul 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/31/07/2024/open-ai-innovation/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="http://rahulmatthan.github.io/images/open-ai-innovation.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>All innovations build on those that came before. It is important to strike a balance between leveraging intellectual property protection for commercial benefit and stifling innovation in the process. And this is particularly relevant in the context of AI.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Idea Factories</title><link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/12/2022/idea-factories/</link><pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/12/2022/idea-factories/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="http://rahulmatthan.github.io/images/idea-factories.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>There are two types of entrepreneurs: &amp;ldquo;Idea Factories,&amp;rdquo; who generate numerous ideas but struggle with execution, and &amp;ldquo;Factories for Ideas,&amp;rdquo; who excel at turning a single idea into a successful business. Recognizing whether an entrepreneur falls into one or the other of these types can help advice them appropriately - and ideally entrepreneurial teams should pair both types for optimal success.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Open Access</title><link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/13/09/2022/open-access/</link><pubDate>Tue, 13 Sep 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/13/09/2022/open-access/</guid><description>&lt;figure>&lt;img src="http://rahulmatthan.github.io/images/open-access.jpg" width="auto">
&lt;/figure>

&lt;p>&lt;em>In the 1600s, scientists collaborated more openly in physics but in secrecy in the field of alchemy. This is probably why physics has continued to this day while alchemy is a dead science. This is why we need open access in modern technology. Shared innovation fosters progress, while secrecy leads to stagnation.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Cycles of Technology</title><link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/06/2022/the-cycles-of-technology/</link><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/06/2022/the-cycles-of-technology/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>We believe that internet platforms are too dominant to fail. But this is not true when you think of the evolution of internet search and curation - suggesting that technology evolves in cycles. We may be on the cusp of a major cyclical transformation - in which case we may challenge the notion that Big Tech is too big to fail.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Problems and Solutions</title><link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/18/05/2022/problems-and-solutions/</link><pubDate>Wed, 18 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/18/05/2022/problems-and-solutions/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>As a reaction to the industrialization of agriculture, particularly the disproportionate land use for livestock, there is growing interest in plant-based meat alternatives. However, even these innovations may have unforeseen consequences, such as deforestation due to increased soy demand. Scientific advancements often solve problems while simultaneously creating new ones, challenging ethical norms and leading to continuous cycles of innovation and adaptation.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Timing is Everything</title><link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/22/02/2022/timing-is-everything/</link><pubDate>Tue, 22 Feb 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/22/02/2022/timing-is-everything/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The success of innovation doesn&amp;rsquo;t correlate directly with statutory or structural impediments, but rather depends on timing and the right set of circumstances. Creating environments conducive to serendipitous connections across unconnected disciplines can foster innovation.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Funding Science</title><link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/18/01/2022/funding-science/</link><pubDate>Tue, 18 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/18/01/2022/funding-science/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Science funding requires patient capital. The NRF should follow 3 principles as it disburses its funding. (i) projects should get long term funding commitments that are protected against political change, (ii) they need operational autonomy so that researchers can follow their own paths and (iii) the NRF should no longer fund government laboratories but focus on finding academia.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Patient Capital</title><link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/23/06/2021/patient-capital/</link><pubDate>Wed, 23 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/23/06/2021/patient-capital/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Breakthroughs in science require patient capital that must be provided by the government. Scientists need to be given a long rope and not be held to the standards of accountability to which we typically hold the government. They need to have bipartisan [[political support]] as they operate at time-scales beyond that which politicians normally function within. They need pipelines to market that will allow these ideas to be naturally commercialised.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Subscribing to Things</title><link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/02/12/2020/subscribing-to-things/</link><pubDate>Wed, 02 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/02/12/2020/subscribing-to-things/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The transition from owning things to subscribing to things is going to be hard until there is widespread market adoption and greater choice. Consumption is central to our economy and the only way we know to consume is by owning things. However once digital distribution becomes seamless we can subscribe to whatever we need to consume whenever we need them.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Bring Back Interoperability</title><link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/03/11/2020/bring-back-interoperability/</link><pubDate>Tue, 03 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/03/11/2020/bring-back-interoperability/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The concept of &amp;ldquo;creative destruction&amp;rdquo; and &amp;ldquo;adversarial interoperability&amp;rdquo; is particularly relevant in the context of modern technology. We need to allow new technologies to work with existing platforms without legal repercussions and foster interoperability.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Leveraging new technologies for development</title><link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/09/2018/leveraging-new-technologies-for-development/</link><pubDate>Wed, 05 Sep 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/09/2018/leveraging-new-technologies-for-development/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Vikram Sarabhai&amp;rsquo;s vision exemplifies India&amp;rsquo;s ability to leapfrog technological generations, learning from global advancements and avoiding their pitfalls, particularly in data technology, healthcare, and urban mobility. It should give us the confidence to shake of path dependence and try new innovative solutions to modern problems.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Where have all the polymaths gone?</title><link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/07/02/2018/where-have-all-the-polymaths-gone/</link><pubDate>Wed, 07 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/07/02/2018/where-have-all-the-polymaths-gone/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Thomas Edison was a prolific inventor because he could find connections between a series of unrelated inventions and ideas. Cross-disciplinary collaboration is critical for innovation and we should guard against the current trend of specialization that may hinder innovation.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>In defence of friction</title><link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/24/01/2018/in-defence-of-friction/</link><pubDate>Wed, 24 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/24/01/2018/in-defence-of-friction/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>To build successful online businesses we need to identify long-standing human desires and use technology to simplify their fulfillment. While technology excels at reducing friction in services like transportation, finance, and shopping, excessive ease can lead to unintended consequences. Regulators face the challenge of balancing technological innovation with necessary legal friction to prevent harm.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>Biology as engineering</title><link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/03/01/2018/biology-as-engineering/</link><pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/03/01/2018/biology-as-engineering/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>Biology&amp;rsquo;s evolution from empirical to engineered, driven by network computing and big data, is revolutionizing healthcare and drug discovery. Innovations like Patient Ping enhance coordinated care, while computational techniques streamline molecule identification, reducing trial and error. Advances in organ-on-a-chip and cell engineering enable more precise, individualized treatments, necessitating a reevaluation of regulatory and intellectual property frameworks.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item><item><title>The Future of Ownership</title><link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/28/06/2017/the-future-of-ownership/</link><pubDate>Wed, 28 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate><guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/28/06/2017/the-future-of-ownership/</guid><description>&lt;p>&lt;em>The shift from private ownership to shared access, particularly in the automobile industry has been remarkable. With the rise of ride-hailing apps and potential for autonomous vehicles, the emphasis on owning a car is diminishing, especially in India, where the culture of vehicle ownership is less ingrained.&lt;/em>&lt;/p></description></item></channel></rss>