<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Maps on Ex Machina</title>
    <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/tags/maps/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Maps on Ex Machina</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://rahulmatthan.github.io/tags/maps/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Big Bad Data</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/11/january/2017/big-bad-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/11/january/2017/big-bad-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The use of data to derive insights about people - whether it be for the purpose of insuring them or assessing the likelihood that they could commit a crime - is a double edged sword. As we look to using data to expand the reach of our financial services we would do well to keep the risks in mind.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Everest Spheroid</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/january/2017/the-everest-spheroid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/january/2017/the-everest-spheroid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The continued reliance by the Government of India to the Everest Spheroid as the reference datum for maps in India is inexplicable considering that modern GPS can now accurately orient itself on the Earth&amp;rsquo;s centre of mass. Which is why their reluctance to modernise map regulations is so inexplicable.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where Did Our Map Regulations Come From</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/17/august/2016/where-did-our-map-regulations-come-from/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/17/august/2016/where-did-our-map-regulations-come-from/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;India&amp;rsquo;s map regulations are set out in the Map Policy of 2005 - a loosely worded quasi-legislative document that is the closest we have to a map law. But the notifications that are referenced in the policy date back to a time before digital maps and as such should not be used to regulate the export of map data.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What the New Geospatial Bill Means for You</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/may/2016/what-the-new-geospatial-bill-means-for-you/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/may/2016/what-the-new-geospatial-bill-means-for-you/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The provisions of the proposed Geospatial Bill should be no surprise as these obligations have formed part of the map policy that has existed for a very long time. But thanks to the government&amp;rsquo;s approach of being outwardly strict in legislation but practically benevolent in enforcement our map ecosystem has flourished.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
