<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Social Media on Ex Machina</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/social-media/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Social Media on Ex Machina</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/social-media/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Sufficient Decentralisation</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/07/12/2022/sufficient-decentralisation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/07/12/2022/sufficient-decentralisation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/sufficient-decentralisation.jpg&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We need to think about creating &amp;ldquo;sufficiently decentralized&amp;rdquo; social networks. While decentralization offers more control to users, it has drawbacks - such as non-unique usernames across the network. If we can use smart contracts to create a decentralized name registry we might be able to balance user control and functionality, and create a more user-empowered internet.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Federated Social Media</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/16/11/2022/federated-social-media/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/16/11/2022/federated-social-media/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://localhost:1313/images/federated-social-media.jpg&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;&gt;&#xA;&lt;/figure&gt;&#xA;&#xA;&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Elon Musk&amp;rsquo;s takeover of Twitter has reignited debates on content moderation and free speech. But today it is not content that is the challenge but context. We need to move from centralized platforms to federated, protocol-based networks, allowing user-controlled, context-sensitive conversations. This is a model already successful in India&amp;rsquo;s digital public infrastructure. digital public infrastructure content moderation context data governance.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Context is King</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/03/05/2022/context-is-king/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 May 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/03/05/2022/context-is-king/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There is a crisis of context in modern information consumption. While data is abundant, understanding its significance requires context. And context is scarce. This leads to misunderstandings and potnetial manipulation of content across a number of fields, including legal education and public communication.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Big Tech &#43; Media Bargain</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/23/02/2021/the-big-tech--media-bargain/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/23/02/2021/the-big-tech--media-bargain/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Australia&amp;rsquo;s media bargaining law that requires digital platforms to share revenues with Australian news companies only allows companies that deal in core news to enter into these revenue-share agreements. This excludes smaller publications and those that provide non-news content. Digital platforms decoupled content from distribution allowing small content providers to reach larger audiences. The Australian legislation will reverse this trend by supporting big new at the cost of independent content providers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The rise of TikTok and regulatory eyebrows in the US</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/25/12/2019/the-rise-of-tiktok-and-regulatory-eyebrows-in-the-us/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/25/12/2019/the-rise-of-tiktok-and-regulatory-eyebrows-in-the-us/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;TikTok&amp;rsquo;s rapid growth has led to scrutiny and opposition from the West, particularly the US, over concerns related to content moderation and data privacy. The US government&amp;rsquo;s anxiety over not being able to directly regulate TikTok&amp;rsquo;s data collection may lead to new regulations, potentially influencing how other governments approach the issue.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The value of scepticism in the age of deep-fake videos</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/18/12/2019/the-value-of-scepticism-in-the-age-of-deep-fake-videos/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/18/12/2019/the-value-of-scepticism-in-the-age-of-deep-fake-videos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With the rise of hyper-realistic deepfakes, discerning truth becomes harder. We need to learn to be more skeptical of the content we receive and constantly question its authenticity. Its not hard to do as we have done this before.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Why our attempt to escape online outrage might fail</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/13/11/2019/why-our-attempt-to-escape-online-outrage-might-fail/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Nov 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/13/11/2019/why-our-attempt-to-escape-online-outrage-might-fail/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;A mass exodus from Twitter to Mastodon in India occurred last week, driven by dissatisfaction with the platform. The migration was sparked by the suspension of lawyer Sanjay Hegde&amp;rsquo;s Twitter account and users are seeking a more respectful environment for debate on Mastodon.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>End-to-end encryption must be retained at all cost</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/28/08/2019/end-to-end-encryption-must-be-retained-at-all-cost/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Aug 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/28/08/2019/end-to-end-encryption-must-be-retained-at-all-cost/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Stripping away anonymity entirely from social media platforms will never ever be useful. Just because a few have taken advantage of online anonymity for nefarious purposes does not mean that everyone else should be denied the many benefits that technology platforms provide.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The government and Big Tech need to meet halfway</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/12/06/2019/the-government-and-big-tech-need-to-meet-halfway/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/12/06/2019/the-government-and-big-tech-need-to-meet-halfway/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;India&amp;rsquo;s new IT minister, Ravi Shankar Prasad, has warned social media companies against misuse of their platforms for terrorism and communalism. The statement highlights a divisive debate between national security advocates and privacy proponents. A balanced approach is needed, with tech companies and law enforcement agencies moderating their stances to ensure both security and privacy.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Technology is making us less open to divergent views</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/20/02/2019/technology-is-making-us-less-open-to-divergent-views/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/20/02/2019/technology-is-making-us-less-open-to-divergent-views/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social interactions have shifted from avoiding political and religious discussions to embracing them, as people now surround themselves with like-minded individuals. Social media platforms enable users to mute differing opinions, reinforcing their existing beliefs. We need to consciously engage with diverse viewpoints rather than allowing technology to further entrench tribal behaviors.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>For the digital world, customer is truly king</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/13/02/2019/for-the-digital-world-customer-is-truly-king/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/13/02/2019/for-the-digital-world-customer-is-truly-king/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Over the past five years, the internet has seen the growth of large technology platforms in various sectors, leading to concerns about competition. Social media and aggregator platforms create a lock-in effect, where users and suppliers feel compelled to join popular platforms, leading to potential monopolies. Traditional competition law views monopolies as harmful, but these platforms challenge this view by improving consumer choice and service quality. However, this shift in market dynamics may harm smaller suppliers, suggesting a need for regulatory protection for these market participants.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Restoring the original vision of the internet</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/10/10/2018/restoring-the-original-vision-of-the-internet/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/10/10/2018/restoring-the-original-vision-of-the-internet/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The modern internet has become centralized and controlled by a few powerful corporations, deviating from its original vision of an open and decentralized platform. Tim Berners-Lee, the founding father of the internet, is working on a project called Solid to restore power to users by allowing them to store personal information in personal data stores (PDS) under their control. That said, universally accepted standards for electronic consent and true social graph portability might be a more effective way to balance convenience and data protection.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The psychology of hate</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/27/09/2017/the-psychology-of-hate/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/27/09/2017/the-psychology-of-hate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The psychology of hate and dehumanization shows that a lack of social contact between different groups can lead to radical biases. The internet&amp;rsquo;s role in social interaction has eroded empathy and increased division, leading to a rise in hate and violence.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Needed: A Fact Rank Algorithm to Flag Fake News</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/19/08/2017/needed-a-fact-rank-algorithm-to-flag-fake-news/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/19/08/2017/needed-a-fact-rank-algorithm-to-flag-fake-news/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Historically, false news has influenced major events, from anti-Semitic libels to the Spanish-American War. With the rise of social media, exposure to unregulated, biased news has increased, exploiting human tendencies like implicit and confirmation biases. This creates echo chambers, reinforcing beliefs without exposure to differing views. The evolution of fake news now includes realistic audio and potential video fabrications. Addressing this, technology, not regulation, might offer solutions, such as a &amp;ldquo;FactRank&amp;rdquo; algorithm to assess news accuracy, akin to Google&amp;rsquo;s PageRank for search results.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Movement of Ideas</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/06/04/2017/the-movement-of-ideas/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 06 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/06/04/2017/the-movement-of-ideas/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There are parallels to be drawn between Martin Luther&amp;rsquo;s use of printing technology and modern communication technologies. Technology has historically accelerated the dissemination of ideas and we need to adapt that understanding to new mediums like the internet.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Algorithmic Oversight</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/21/09/2016/algorithmic-oversight/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/21/09/2016/algorithmic-oversight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Social media news algorithms represent the future of news dissemination. However, the need for personalization, driven by advertising revenue, creates &amp;lsquo;filter bubbles&amp;rsquo;, limiting our exposure to a diversity of information sources. We need to implement software oversight: open-source algorithms auditing newsfeeds for bias, maintaining algorithm secrecy while ensuring objectivity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The New News</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/20/07/2016/the-new-news/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/20/07/2016/the-new-news/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There is a transformation in the dissemination of news now that it takes place through social media platforms and smartphones. As a result user-generated content has started to shape modern journalism. As a result there is a shift in the role of social media companies that raises new questions about the protection and support for this new form of citizen journalism.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
