<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Intellectual Property on Ex Machina</title>
    <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/tags/intellectual-property/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Intellectual Property on Ex Machina</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://rahulmatthan.github.io/tags/intellectual-property/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Does AI Copy</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/15/02/2023/does-ai-copy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/15/02/2023/does-ai-copy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Generative AI has had a transformative impact on text and visual arts. While the AI&amp;rsquo;s ability to mimic artistic styles raises copyright concerns, does this constitutes &amp;ldquo;copying&amp;rdquo;? How will the definition of artistic talent evolve in the AI era?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rethinking Patents</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/30/08/2022/rethinking-patents/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 30 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/30/08/2022/rethinking-patents/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The PM-EAC has recommended reforms to India&amp;rsquo;s patent system that primarily involved ramping up the work force (from about 800 to 2800 in a couple of years) and also introducing the utility system of patents as appropriate. I suggest we go a bit further and try and tweak the term of patent so that it is more appropriate for the invention being protected. So 20 years for pharma but no more than 5 for tech patents that in any event evolve to the next generation within that time.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Colour Me Purple</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/02/08/2022/colour-me-purple/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 02 Aug 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/02/08/2022/colour-me-purple/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Intellectual property boundaries are being streteched with companies claiming exclusive rights over specific colors and the extension of copyright terms. Its time for a re-evaluation of how intangible property is protected, given modern technologies and commercial realities.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ring Fencing</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/26/07/2022/ring-fencing/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 26 Jul 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/26/07/2022/ring-fencing/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There is a parallel between the use of barbed wire in the American prairies to establish property rights and the modern challenge of protecting intangible assets like intellectual property. Barbed wire allowed landowners to enforce title by fencing off land instead of branding ownership onto cattle. Decentralized technologies, such as blockchain, could transform the way intangible assets are protected, just like erecting fences around real estate, made it inherently resistant to trespass.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Should AI own IP</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/27/10/2021/should-ai-own-ip/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/27/10/2021/should-ai-own-ip/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The South African patent office has granted a patent to an artificial intelligence program for an invention it has made. India granted a copyright to an AI application along similar lines. It is not clear how an artificial intelligence can exercise the IP granted by prosecuting a breach or negotiating commercial arrangements for its license. All these actions will have to be taken by humans on behalf of the AI in which case what is the point in calling the algorithm an inventor.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Let’s update the notion of ownership to the digital age</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/12/02/2020/lets-update-the-notion-of-ownership-to-the-digital-age/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/12/02/2020/lets-update-the-notion-of-ownership-to-the-digital-age/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology enables us to use things we do not own but unless laws change from regulating based on ownership to regulating based on access despite everything our technology has made possible, innovation will continue to be stifled by legislation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Biology as engineering</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/03/01/2018/biology-as-engineering/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/03/01/2018/biology-as-engineering/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Biology&amp;rsquo;s evolution from empirical to engineered, driven by network computing and big data, is revolutionizing healthcare and drug discovery. Innovations like Patient Ping enhance coordinated care, while computational techniques streamline molecule identification, reducing trial and error. Advances in organ-on-a-chip and cell engineering enable more precise, individualized treatments, necessitating a reevaluation of regulatory and intellectual property frameworks.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cutting out the Middleman</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/08/06/2017/cutting-out-the-middleman/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 08 Jun 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/08/06/2017/cutting-out-the-middleman/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Music&amp;rsquo;s evolution from live performances to digital streaming has been shaped by technology, expanding audience reach but often at the cost of artist revenue. With the advent of blockchain-based services like Musicoin, artists can now bypass traditional intermediaries, offering direct access to their music and potentially transforming the industry&amp;rsquo;s revenue model.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Remix Generation</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/10/2016/the-remix-generation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/10/2016/the-remix-generation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Delhi high court&amp;rsquo;s decision allowing photocopying of textbooks for educational purposes has been praised for its modern interpretation of copyright law. The ruling emphasizes the need to adapt copyright law to contemporary realities, including the rise of digital content and remix culture, where traditional copyright may hinder creativity.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Artist and his Audience</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/15/09/2016/the-artist-and-his-audience/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/15/09/2016/the-artist-and-his-audience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The history of copyright reflects the struggle of artists to reach audiences, from direct personal interfaces to the printing press and the Internet. Despite the symbiotic relationship between artists and publishers, the Internet has allowed artists to directly access audiences. Recent amendments to India&amp;rsquo;s Copyright Act and government clarifications have further extended the scope to Internet broadcasting companies, potentially unlocking vast music catalogues, though the direct benefit to artists remains unclear.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
