<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Ex Machina</title>
    <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/posts/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Ex Machina</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 17:17:58 +0530</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://rahulmatthan.github.io/posts/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Momentous Change</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/january/2023/momentous-change/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 17:17:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/january/2023/momentous-change/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We are potentially on the verge of momentous change. Artificial intelligence has improved to the point where it could pass as human. As a result, the search technology that was responsible for so much of the modern internet is facing its strongest challenge and with it the business model of the internet as we know it is under threat.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Looking Back</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/28/december/2022/looking-back/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2022 17:17:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/28/december/2022/looking-back/</guid>
      <description>In my very first article of the year I predicted that 2022 would be a busy year for tech policy. I was basing my prediction on the progress that had been made so far on our draft privacy law - the fact that now that the Joint Parliamentary Committee had finally submitted its draft, it seemed inevitable that the bill was well on its way to becoming a law. I saw the immediate next steps as being crucial - the establishment of the Data Protection Authority, the creation of rules, regulations and codes of practice and the daunting task of orienting commercial practice around a new culture of compliance.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Idea Factories</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/december/2022/idea-factories/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2022 17:17:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/december/2022/idea-factories/</guid>
      <description>Over the course of my career, I have come across entrepreneurs of all hues.
Some are bubbling with inspiration, constantly finding solutions to the problems around them. They have an almost inexhaustible supply of ideas and the energy and inclination to worry away at a problem till they’ve figured out how to solve it. They love to mend what’s broken in the world—the problems no one else has been able to solve.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Truth and LLMs</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/14/december/2022/truth-and-llms/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2022 17:17:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/14/december/2022/truth-and-llms/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If the purpose of education is to equip the younger generation with the skills they need to face the challenges of the world they are growing into, it is important to constantly re-evaluate the role that technology will play in that future. While we must not expect the skill of the past to continue to be useful we should guard against trusting technology blindly.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regulatory Sandbox</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/25/january/2017/regulatory-sandbox/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/25/january/2017/regulatory-sandbox/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;If we can we should test the effect of new regulations in a sandboxed environment to understand what the consequences of enacting a new legislation could be. And if we do this perhaps we will be able to make our legislations a bit more precise.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rare Diseases: Orphan Drugs</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/18/january/2017/rare-diseases-orphan-drugs/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/18/january/2017/rare-diseases-orphan-drugs/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There are some diseases that afflict such a small percentage of the population that pharmaceutical companies do not have the commercial incentive to discover the drugs to cure them. Or if they do, they price it so high that it is unaffordable. We need a policy approach to ensure that orphan drugs like these get to those who need them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Big Bad Data</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/11/january/2017/big-bad-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/11/january/2017/big-bad-data/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The use of data to derive insights about people - whether it be for the purpose of insuring them or assessing the likelihood that they could commit a crime - is a double edged sword. As we look to using data to expand the reach of our financial services we would do well to keep the risks in mind.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Everest Spheroid</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/january/2017/the-everest-spheroid/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/january/2017/the-everest-spheroid/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The continued reliance by the Government of India to the Everest Spheroid as the reference datum for maps in India is inexplicable considering that modern GPS can now accurately orient itself on the Earth&amp;rsquo;s centre of mass. Which is why their reluctance to modernise map regulations is so inexplicable.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Digital Inclusion for the 85%</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/28/december/2016/digital-inclusion-for-the-85/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/28/december/2016/digital-inclusion-for-the-85/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Machines are about to breach the last threshold that humanity had always believed would be its sole preserve - the cerebral bastion. If we are to continue retain the upper hand we will need to change our very approach to education to make it more reflective of the changing times.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Day the Machines Take Over</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/december/2016/the-day-the-machines-take-over/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/december/2016/the-day-the-machines-take-over/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Machines are about to breach the last threshold that humanity had always believed would be its sole preserve - the cerebral bastion. If we are to continue retain the upper hand we will need to change our very approach to education to make it more reflective of the changing times.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Cutting the Code</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/23/november/2016/cutting-the-code/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/23/november/2016/cutting-the-code/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;CRISPR offers us the opportunity to eliminate a number of genetic diseases that cause untold human suffering. That said, the ethics of carrying out such radical alterations to our DNA need to be considered at every step. But even so, if we have the opportunity to eliminate huma suffering are we not obliged to at least give it a shot?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Coveillance</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/november/2016/coveillance/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 16 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/november/2016/coveillance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Advances in technology have changed our notions of privacy and what we need to do to protect it. In today&amp;rsquo;s world saturated surveillance is inevitable. Our only chance to restore the balance is to develop an approach that ensures that the watchers are also being watched.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The New Imperialists</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/09/november/2016/the-new-imperialists/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/09/november/2016/the-new-imperialists/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In order for new technologies to take hold we have often offered the companies that operate them special exemptions. This has allowed them to build vast commercial networks that they exert extraordinary influence over the world. These are the real imperialists and unless we remain vigilant history will repeat itself.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rise of the Machines</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/02/november/2016/rise-of-the-machines/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/02/november/2016/rise-of-the-machines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We should regulate autonomous weapons like we govern nuclear non-proliferation and climate change - through international consensus and not national policy. If we build machine intelligence that can decide who to kill this technology we will not be able to control whose hands this gets into.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regtech Will Change the Way we Regulate</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/26/october/2016/regtech-will-change-the-way-we-regulate/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/26/october/2016/regtech-will-change-the-way-we-regulate/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As we begin to increasingly use more and more technology for compliance we will inevitably graduate to a more proactive approach. API-driven compliance will allow regulators to directly connect to regulated entities so that relevant compliance information can be collected on a real-time basis.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quantified Self</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/19/october/2016/quantified-self/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 19 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/19/october/2016/quantified-self/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As wearable devices and constant monitoring technologies change the nature of the health data we have access to there is an opportunity to change the way we think of medicine - from the ways in which we diagnose to how we treat disease. But this will require us to make changes to our regulatory frameworks around diagnosis and drug discovery.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Remix Generation</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/october/2016/the-remix-generation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 05 Oct 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/october/2016/the-remix-generation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We need to re-imagine our copyright laws to update it to the modern era. As new technologies democratise access to content and remove barriers between the artist and his audience we need to find new legal solutions for the remix generation.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Database of our Maladies</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/28/september/2016/database-of-our-maladies/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/28/september/2016/database-of-our-maladies/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;India is about to build a new healthcare data systems from scratch. This is an opportunity to make sure that we do nto make the mistakes that healthcare data systems in other countries suffer from. We should make sure that patients not only own their data within these systems, they also have access to them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Algorithmic Oversight</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/september/2016/algorithmic-oversight/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/september/2016/algorithmic-oversight/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is next to impossible to avoid the increasing personalisation of the internet. As more and more businesses look to understand their client better by personalising their services to them lawmakers have begun to look into the consequences of these actions. Could we develop software solutions for regulatory oversight so that we fight fire with fire?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Artist and his Audience</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/15/september/2016/the-artist-and-his-audience/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 15 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/15/september/2016/the-artist-and-his-audience/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Technology has democratised distribution of content allowing a more direct connection between artists and their audience. New amendments in India&amp;rsquo;s copyright laws have taken this even further ensuring that creative works are even more accessible than they have ever been.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data is a Capital Asset</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/09/september/2016/data-is-a-capital-asset/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 09 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/09/september/2016/data-is-a-capital-asset/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The insights we derive from data could help with governance in new and interesting ways. While they are already being used to predict crime what if instead of forcing companies and businesses to report their compliance, governments use data insights to predict it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Can We Do Without Cash</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/01/september/2016/can-we-do-without-cash/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 01 Sep 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/01/september/2016/can-we-do-without-cash/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This article was written shortly after the launch of UPI, India&amp;rsquo;s fast payment system. At the time no-one really knew how this new system was going to work and I had some fanciful dieas of what we could do to ensure that this new payments system did not go the way of those that have come before it.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Evolution of Identity</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/24/august/2016/the-evolution-of-identity/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 24 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/24/august/2016/the-evolution-of-identity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Anonymity on the internet allows trolls to operate without filters - leaving them free to plumb depths that they would not have been able to in real life. Voluntarily identifying oneself in order to ensure that the content you put out is directly associated with your identity offers.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Where Did Our Map Regulations Come From</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/17/august/2016/where-did-our-map-regulations-come-from/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 17 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/17/august/2016/where-did-our-map-regulations-come-from/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;India&amp;rsquo;s map regulations are set out in the Map Policy of 2005 - a loosely worded quasi-legislative document that is the closest we have to a map law. But the notifications that are referenced in the policy date back to a time before digital maps and as such should not be used to regulate the export of map data.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Lazy Legislation</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/10/august/2016/lazy-legislation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/10/august/2016/lazy-legislation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Regulators today, are struggling to come to terms with the transformations that society is going through. As a result, the regulations they draft are often loosely worded to account for variations they cannot envisage. This is forcing businesses to adopt new and complex business models as they try to comply.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>From Ownership to Access</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/03/august/2016/from-ownership-to-access/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Aug 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/03/august/2016/from-ownership-to-access/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We have grown accustomed to constant consumption that has been made possible by planned obsolescence. But new technologies have made it possible for us to make the shift from ownership to access. Will this reverse the trend of constant consumption?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Tech to ensure Data Symmetry</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/27/july/2016/using-tech-to-ensure-data-symmetry/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/27/july/2016/using-tech-to-ensure-data-symmetry/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Information asymmetry has always been a challenge for market economics. But the new knowledge economy has eliminated much of that imperfection allowing buyers and sellers to be better aware of all the relevant information before making their decisions. In which case can we now use technology instead of regulation to adress these ills.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The New News</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/20/july/2016/the-new-news/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/20/july/2016/the-new-news/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Internet has radically transformed the way in which the news reaches us. The news organisations that used to assume the role of gatekeepers of news content are no longer in control of what we get to see. But can social media companies that have enabled citizen journalism assume the responsibility that news organisations used to display.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Blockchain Governance</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/13/july/2016/blockchain-governance/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 13 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/13/july/2016/blockchain-governance/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The idea behind the concept of the blockchain and a distributed ledger can be applied in so many ways otehr than the bitcoin use case that it is most popularly known for. We need to think of how it can be used for smart contracts and novel governance usecases.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Demise of the Artisanal Lawyer</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/july/2016/the-demise-of-the-artisanal-lawyer/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Jul 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/july/2016/the-demise-of-the-artisanal-lawyer/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The changes wrought by modern computational technologies seem to be far more fundamental than any that have come before it. The legal profession is not immune from these changes. What will change first are the clerical jobs that fresh associates are assigned as a way to learn on the job. What will we do to train our workforce once these jobs are performed by machines?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Accountability Framework</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/29/june/2016/accountability-framework/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/29/june/2016/accountability-framework/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Consent based regulation has not been particularly successful when it comes to protecting privacy. Instead of getting corporations to take our consent before they process our data we would do well to make them more accountable for their actions and the harms that befall us when the process our data indiscriminately.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Drone Traffic Laws</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/22/june/2016/drone-traffic-laws/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/22/june/2016/drone-traffic-laws/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Commercial drones are likely to be flown in urban areas. If that is the case, isn&amp;rsquo;t it better that, instead of being regulated by the DGCA, they come under the jurisdiction of the police will will need to address the traffic management and privacy violation issues that are likely to arise?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Ethics of Automation</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/june/2016/ethics-of-automation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/june/2016/ethics-of-automation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We need to develop the ethical frameworks within which vehicle manufacturers should operate or else they will ensure that the parameters on which autonomous vehicles are regulated serve their own interests. Autonomous vehicles should not have to comply with laws designed for vehicles are driven by humans.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Trusting the Sharing Economy</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/08/june/2016/trusting-the-sharing-economy/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jun 2016 17:17:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/08/june/2016/trusting-the-sharing-economy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;On-demand services that comprise the sharing economy are superior to their real world counterparts because of the dual feedback system. Trust identity based on dual feedback loops could create the civilised commercial ecosystem that has always been the ultimate objective of putting in place a regulatory framework.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>What the New Geospatial Bill Means for You</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/may/2016/what-the-new-geospatial-bill-means-for-you/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 May 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/may/2016/what-the-new-geospatial-bill-means-for-you/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The provisions of the proposed Geospatial Bill should be no surprise as these obligations have formed part of the map policy that has existed for a very long time. But thanks to the government&amp;rsquo;s approach of being outwardly strict in legislation but practically benevolent in enforcement our map ecosystem has flourished.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Stiff Backbone of the Aadhaar Act</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/24/march/2016/the-stiff-backbone-of-the-aadhaar-act/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2016 17:17:58 +0530</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/24/march/2016/the-stiff-backbone-of-the-aadhaar-act/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;While it is not without its flaws, the Aadhaar Act imposes some of the strongest fetters on government over-reach of any legislation in the country.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/01/january/1/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/01/january/1/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
