<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Geopolitics of Technology on Ex Machina</title>
    <link>http://localhost:1313/tags/geopolitics-of-technology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Geopolitics of Technology on Ex Machina</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://localhost:1313/tags/geopolitics-of-technology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>India’s 21st century dilemma of global non-alignment</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/22/07/2020/indias-21st-century-dilemma-of-global-non-alignment/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/22/07/2020/indias-21st-century-dilemma-of-global-non-alignment/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;India will need to remain non-aligned as it did during the Cold War unless it ups its game and becomes the third force in the two way battle. In the new tech cold war between US and China, India cannot remain non-aligned.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>How Britain got ahead of us in economic development</title>
      <link>http://localhost:1313/08/01/2020/how-britain-got-ahead-of-us-in-economic-development/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 08 Jan 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://localhost:1313/08/01/2020/how-britain-got-ahead-of-us-in-economic-development/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;By substituting wood with coal England to achieve a far higher energy utilization and lower the cost of manufacture of iron and steel, generating large amounts of ferrous products and bringing into the production process a level of industrialization that India could not. Since cotton was a valuable trade commodity, effort was invested into producing textiles, resulting in the discovery of new means of production that launched the industrial revolution. This resulted in a loss of demand for various other goods whose continued development would have increased the pace of technological innovation in India. It translated into the destruction of educational institutions that generated knowledge and reduced the patronage for scientific and technical inquiry.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
