<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Autonomous Technology on Ex Machina</title>
    <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/tags/autonomous-technology/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Autonomous Technology on Ex Machina</description>
    <generator>Hugo</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://rahulmatthan.github.io/tags/autonomous-technology/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The perilous consequences of automation dependency</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/26/06/2019/the-perilous-consequences-of-automation-dependency/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Jun 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/26/06/2019/the-perilous-consequences-of-automation-dependency/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The crash of Air France Flight 447 in 2009 highlights the dangers of over-reliance on automation in aviation. When the autopilot disengaged due to a malfunction, the pilots&amp;rsquo; lack of manual flying experience led to a fatal error. But counter-intuitively - rather than relying on human intervention we need to trust more in machines and building better systems to automate them.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Autonomous transportation at scale is here</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/15/08/2018/autonomous-transportation-at-scale-is-here/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/15/08/2018/autonomous-transportation-at-scale-is-here/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There has been a swift rise in autonomous vehicles on roads. This rapid growth necessitates urgent regulation, particularly around ethical programming decisions and societal impacts. The transition to autonomous vehicles will significantly alter urban life and labor markets, potentially leading to urban segregation and widespread unemployment as human drivers are replaced by robots, underscoring the need for thoughtful societal and regulatory responses to this technological evolution.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Will humans be part of the wars of the future?</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/23/05/2018/will-humans-be-part-of-the-wars-of-the-future/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 May 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/23/05/2018/will-humans-be-part-of-the-wars-of-the-future/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;There are inherrent challenges of using autonomous weapons with human oversight - in particular the fact that human judgment becomes an &amp;ldquo;inconvenient impediment&amp;rdquo; to the speed of modern warfare. Future wars, especially in the cybernetic arena, may render human intervention meaningless - and that should raise ethical and practical concerns.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Unintended consequences of autonomous transportation</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/06/12/2017/unintended-consequences-of-autonomous-transportation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 06 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/06/12/2017/unintended-consequences-of-autonomous-transportation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Urban mobility is on the brink of transformation with the convergence of on-demand transport, electric engines, and autonomous vehicles. This shift could lead to the end of car ownership, fossil fuel-powered vehicles, and traditional traffic management. It may also free up urban space, reduce transportation costs, and allow India, with its low automobile ownership, to lead this revolution with forward-looking policies and infrastructure development.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>War of the machines</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/29/11/2017/war-of-the-machines/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/29/11/2017/war-of-the-machines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The emerging threat of autonomous drones equipped with facial recognition and AI technologies raises new concerns when it comes to the future of warfare. The moral and ethical concerns of fully autonomous weapons calls for an international agreement to ban such technology, akin to the ban on biological weapons.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>Ready for the day the Machines Take Over</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/12/2016/ready-for-the-day-the-machines-take-over/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/12/2016/ready-for-the-day-the-machines-take-over/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As cognitive machines begin to take over human decision-making functions, there is an urgent need to redesign education to promote creative thought and problem-solving. Without these changes, the next generation may be ill-equipped to stay ahead of the machines, risking being overwhelmed by technological advancements.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Rise of the Machines</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/02/11/2016/the-rise-of-the-machines/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 02 Nov 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/02/11/2016/the-rise-of-the-machines/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We should regulate autonomous weapons like we govern nuclear non-proliferation and climate change - through international consensus and not national policy. If we build machine intelligence that can decide who to kill this technology we will not be able to control whose hands this gets into.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    <item>
      <title>The Ethics of Automation</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/06/2016/the-ethics-of-automation/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Jun 2016 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/16/06/2016/the-ethics-of-automation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We need to develop the ethical frameworks within which vehicle manufacturers should operate or else they will ensure that the parameters on which autonomous vehicles are regulated serve their own interests. Autonomous vehicles should not have to comply with laws designed for vehicles are driven by humans.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
  </channel>
</rss>
