<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Content Moderation on Ex Machina</title>
    <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/tags/content-moderation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Content Moderation on Ex Machina</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://rahulmatthan.github.io/tags/content-moderation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>The Loss of Immunity</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/09/2024/the-loss-of-immunity/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 05 Sep 2024 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/05/09/2024/the-loss-of-immunity/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://rahulmatthan.github.io/images/the-loss-of-immunity.jpg&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;While the world has been agog with the news of the arrest of the CEO of Telegram followed in quick succession by the decision to boot X (formerly Twitter) out of Brazil, a decision in the US is likely to have a much more far-reaching impact on how content is delivered online.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moderating Systems</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/10/05/2023/moderating-systems/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 May 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/10/05/2023/moderating-systems/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://rahulmatthan.github.io/images/moderating-systems.png&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Content moderation challenges arise from the vast volume of online content and diverse user beliefs. Current moderation uses automated tools and human moderators, but both have flaws. Evelyn Douek suggests a &amp;ldquo;systems thinking&amp;rdquo; approach, focusing on systemic solutions rather than individual errors. As India drafts the Digital India Act, a shift towards addressing systemic issues in content moderation is essential.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dis-Content</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/22/02/2023/dis-content/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Feb 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/22/02/2023/dis-content/</guid>
      <description>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&#34;http://rahulmatthan.github.io/images/dis-content.jpg&#34; width=&#34;auto&#34;/&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;In the early internet era, websites were liable for third-party content, leading to legal challenges. US Section 230 was introduced, protecting online platforms from being treated as publishers for user-generated content. However, in Gonzales vs. Google, YouTube&amp;rsquo;s recommendation algorithms are under scrutiny, potentially redefining Section 230&amp;rsquo;s protections. The decision could reshape online content moderation globally.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Appealing Moderation</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/14/06/2022/appealing-moderation/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 14 Jun 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/14/06/2022/appealing-moderation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The draft amendments to the Information Technology Rules, 2021, will require intermediaries to align community standards with Indian law and create a Grievance Appellate Committee for &amp;ldquo;problematic content.&amp;rdquo; Critics view this as a tool of government censorship, while others see a need for balance between government control and private enterprise.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Backfire</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/11/01/2022/backfire/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 11 Jan 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/11/01/2022/backfire/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Any attempt to change the beliefs of vaccine skeptics using facts is bound to fail. Thanks to the backfire effect they will take the facts presented to them and bend them to fit with their beliefs rather than allow new facts to convince them that their beliefs were wrong.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Intermediaries Liable</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/25/05/2021/intermediaries-liable/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/25/05/2021/intermediaries-liable/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Intermediary Guidelines 2021 just make things more confused. It will cover social media intermediaries on the basis of registered users and not active users which can be a big deal for many companies that have a relatively small active Indian user base. It will apply to services that provide messaging as just an ancillary service - and most digital platforms do that. Voluntary verification is also a strange requirement since it doesn&amp;rsquo;t ensure traceability because its not mandatory. Anyone who fails to comply even with the most minor requirements of the regulations will lose their intermediary liability protections.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Gatekeepers at the Edge</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/19/01/2021/gatekeepers-at-the-edge/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 19 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/19/01/2021/gatekeepers-at-the-edge/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;We gave internet companies immunity for the content the flows through their pipes because communication infrastructure should have no opinion on the content. This, however does not solve the problem of offensive content - at best it passes the buck. We need a framework for determining what is acceptable speech. Governments should develop prohibited content dashboards so that internet companies can understand clearly what content is permissible and what is not.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moderating with Moderation</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/28/10/2020/moderating-with-moderation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 28 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/28/10/2020/moderating-with-moderation/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Digital platforms face a number of challenges when it comes to content moderation, particularly when compared with traditional media&amp;rsquo;s editorial oversight. Most platforms adopt an &amp;ldquo;after-the-fact&amp;rdquo; approach to taking-down the content but they may be better off using algorithmic tools to dampen the virality of offensive content without infringing on free speech.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Shield online platforms for content moderation to work</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/03/06/2020/shield-online-platforms-for-content-moderation-to-work/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 03 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/03/06/2020/shield-online-platforms-for-content-moderation-to-work/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I believe the Indian government should introduce Good Samaritan protections in its new Intermediary Guidelines, prosecuting those who negligently allow violative content on their platforms. There is a need for a balanced approach that encourages responsible moderation without stifling free speech.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The value of scepticism in the age of deep-fake videos</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/18/12/2019/the-value-of-scepticism-in-the-age-of-deep-fake-videos/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 18 Dec 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/18/12/2019/the-value-of-scepticism-in-the-age-of-deep-fake-videos/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;With the rise of hyper-realistic deepfakes, discerning truth becomes harder. We need to learn to be more skeptical of the content we receive and constantly question its authenticity. Its not hard to do as we have done this before.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The challenge of detecting fake content</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/11/2018/the-challenge-of-detecting-fake-content/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/11/2018/the-challenge-of-detecting-fake-content/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The information revolution has disrupted traditional media gatekeeping, leading to the unchecked spread of misinformation. The rise of deep fake technology, creating indistinguishable false content, exacerbates this issue. Governments are struggling to regulate, and potential solutions like immutable life logs raise privacy concerns.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>History shows us how to deal with news echo chambers</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/20/06/2018/history-shows-us-how-to-deal-with-news-echo-chambers/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/20/06/2018/history-shows-us-how-to-deal-with-news-echo-chambers/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Benjamin Day published The Sun which was the world&amp;rsquo;s first penny press newspaper that was entirely ad-supported. This gave rise to advertising as a means to support the cost of news. Warren and Brandeis defined the Right to Privacy which contributed to the decline of yellow journalism. We need a similar reconceptualisation of regulation today to address the menace of ad driven news.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The backfire effect and the menace of fake news</title>
      <link>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/02/2018/the-backfire-effect-and-the-menace-of-fake-news/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Feb 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://rahulmatthan.github.io/21/02/2018/the-backfire-effect-and-the-menace-of-fake-news/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The &amp;ldquo;backfire effect&amp;rdquo; is a cognitive bias that causes people to double down on their beliefs despite evidence to the contrary. This makes fake news hard to combat because it taps into regional cultural norms and beliefs, making it resonate deeply with its intended audience. The only effective remedy is to engage with fake news at a subliminal level, recognizing its impact on political views and opinions.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
